<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>COVID-19 on Philotheos</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/covid-19/</link>
    <description>Recent content in COVID-19 on Philotheos</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 May 2021 15:49:36 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/covid-19/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Can You Stream the Lord&#39;s Supper</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/thoughts/can-you-stream-the-supper/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 May 2021 15:49:36 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/thoughts/can-you-stream-the-supper/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;can-you-stream-the-lords-supper&#34;&gt;Can You Stream the Lord&amp;rsquo;s Supper?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing which has troubled me the most about COVID times is the strain it has placed upon areas of Christian theology and practice which have apparently wasted with lack of use &amp;ndash; or which never were strengthened in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly the question of whether an &lt;em&gt;ἐκκλησία&lt;/em&gt; must &lt;em&gt;meet&lt;/em&gt; to qualify as such is one of the most obvious examples of this, but other areas include the general principles around Government reaching into Church practice, how our understanding of Christian liberty (remember that?) should inform our practice, and what I want to think about in this post, what is the degree to which we can malleate the Sacraments without mishaping them so much they lose their form entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;an-overview-of-the-situation&#34;&gt;An overview of the situation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Various Churches and denominations have taken different approaches to this question. The Church of England had a heated debate over whether the Eurcharist could be celebrated with no-one actually present, and for some reason they decided that, contrary to all of their formularies and tradition, an epidemic meant that priests actually could do this. Other more liturgical denominations have taken to delivering elements to congregants ahead of time to be blessed over the Internet. Still others have recommended a Eucharistic fast, as a form of penitence over the removal of access to the Supper and the grace conferred in it. &amp;ldquo;Lower&amp;rdquo; church denominations, more generally focussed on the Word, seem in many cases to have simply told congregants to use blackcurrant cordial and Warbuton&amp;rsquo;s, and to celebrate communion isolated in their bedrooms, enlightened by their screens showing others doing the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was never comfortable with these innovations, and thankfully my Church opted for a slightly different strategy, until a recent lapse. I&amp;rsquo;ve had some thoughts as to how to express those doubts, and a recent discussion between some Lutheran pastors&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; has been helpful to confirm and clarify much of my thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;arguments-against-streaming-the-supper&#34;&gt;Arguments against streaming the Supper&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;from-the-nature-of-a-streamed-gathering&#34;&gt;From the nature of a streamed &amp;ldquo;gathering&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you come together, it is not the Lord’s supper that you eat. (1 Corinthians 11.20)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are actually two forms of gathering to consider. One is the Zoom-fest we have come to love in recent times. The second is that of streaming the service to a different location where some portion of the Body is gathered, be that in an upper room, or a different place.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To answer the first will in large part inform the answer to the second.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;is-an-online-gathering-a-gathering&#34;&gt;Is an online gathering a gathering?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has become very common to describe joining an online video room as &amp;ldquo;meeting&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; Google&amp;rsquo;s product (formerly Hangouts) is literally called Meet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;from-the-regulative-principle&#34;&gt;From the Regulative Principle&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Scripture defines what we do in our worship services.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;words-of-institution&#34;&gt;Words of Institution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;23 For I received from the Lord what I also delivered to you, that the Lord Jesus on the night when he was betrayed took bread, 24 and when he had given thanks, he broke it, and said, “This is my body which is for you. Do this in remembrance of me.” 25 In the same way also he took the cup, after supper, saying, “This cup is the new covenant in my blood. Do this, as often as you drink it, in remembrance of me.” 26 For as often as you eat this bread and drink the cup, you proclaim the Lord&amp;rsquo;s death until he comes. (1 Corinthians 11.23-26)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;apparently-random-liturgical-changes&#34;&gt;Apparently Random Liturgical Changes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the troubling aspects I have seen more generally in these times is the apparently random changes implemented for the sake of it, and this has even bled into Church practice. Why is this unwise?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a well known saying that &lt;em&gt;lex orandi, lex credendi&lt;/em&gt;, and the underlying reason for this is that we inherently assume that other people are acting with a valid end (telos) in view, and if a change is being made, it is towards that valid and good end. In the context of Church practice, the assumption in the mind of the congregant is that the change, whatever it is, must be being made because it more closely aligns with God&amp;rsquo;s will on the matter. But if that is the case, then an account has to be made as to why the new practice is more closely aligned with God&amp;rsquo;s holy will, and if no account is given, we enter the mired territory of superstition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You used to stand up to sing, but now you stand up for the Gospel reading? Kneeling is no longer permitted? The elements of the Supper are pre-distributed? They are consumed immediately and individually rather than together?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are all changes to practice which may or may not be substantive, but at least they require some justification to be communicated to the people. Any time a bodily position is changed in a service, it is a significant thing, and standing for a thing for which one ordinarily would remain seated needs more than an implicit &amp;ldquo;due to Coronavirus&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/usG1bKuWZ-I&#34;&gt;https://youtu.be/usG1bKuWZ-I&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is striking to note how much of the Reformed Church has always been against any form of multi-site streamed Church, and yet has so uncritically accepted this new form of, well, multi-site streamed Church.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2LBCF Chapter 22: Of Religious Worship and the Sabbath Day&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.arbca.com/1689-chapter22&#34;&gt;https://www.arbca.com/1689-chapter22&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
      
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

