<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Baptism on Philotheos</title>
    <link>https://philotheos.de/tags/baptism/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Baptism on Philotheos</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2024 21:35:24 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://philotheos.de/tags/baptism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Wherein the Party Is to Be Baptized</title>
      <link>https://philotheos.de/thoughts/wherein-the-party-is-to-be-baptized/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2024 21:35:24 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philotheos.de/thoughts/wherein-the-party-is-to-be-baptized/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;LBCF 29.3: &amp;ldquo;The outward element to be used in this ordinance is water, wherein the party is to be baptized, in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are three elements to this Article:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The outward element of water.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The naming of the act as &amp;ldquo;Baptism&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The invocation of the Triune Name (in the singular).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conversion into a formula is the standard &amp;ldquo;I baptize you in the Name &amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; whilst physically using ordinary water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have not seen discussion of the baptismal formula in Particular Baptist writings since the common formula was universally received. This Article is itself largely pinched directly from Westminster which prescribed the standard English formula in the &lt;em&gt;Directory&lt;/em&gt;, and it is highly unlikely anyone ventured to veer from this straight and sure path, though it is equally certain that many (with some exceptions) of the Particular Baptists were such precisely because they had a lower sacramental and scholastic style of theologizing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-the-outward-element&#34;&gt;I. The Outward Element&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If water is not used, Baptism is not realized. Discussions of baptism in sand, mud, spittle, and all such nonsense are wholly without warrant. Ordinary water, blessed if you wish, is the outward matter of the Sacrament.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ii-the-naming-of-the-act&#34;&gt;II. The Naming of the Act&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The naming of the act as Baptism is necessary to distinguish the act of washing from any other washing. Baptism is a ritual, and thus it must be announced that the ritual is taking place by means of words of common signification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to ask the first generation Baptists their opinion, but to me it seems necessary that the words used to signify Baptism as taking place presently must be linguistically coherent in order for the act itself to be signified. Deviations from the formula may retain validity, but not all deviations may.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;I cleanse you&amp;rdquo; may be OK.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;I christen you&amp;rdquo; was popular in early modern English and is readily understood, but is probably to be avoided.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;I wash you&amp;rdquo; is probably OK, but kind of weird.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, one which has seen increasing occurrence over the past few decades should be avoided: &amp;ldquo;We baptize you&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reasons are based on the consideration that Baptism can only be performed by one person, or is actually only performed by one person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Baptism is a sacramental act, and the one baptizing the body perfects the act alone.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It cannot be half-completed by one and half-completed by another, but this is the only way two can co-operate in a physical cause.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thus &amp;ldquo;we&amp;rdquo; referring to multiple dippers signifies the intention not to perform a full Baptism.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But the intention not to give a full Baptism contradicts Christ&amp;rsquo;s intention to give a full Baptism by means of the physical Baptism given.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thus a failure to give a full physical Baptism frustrates a full spiritual Baptism and renders the act void.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If &amp;ldquo;we&amp;rdquo; referes to the minister and Christ, then Baptism has not been signified.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is because Baptism as signified by the minister must refer to the physical Baptism with water.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The minister in no wise participates in Christ&amp;rsquo;s Baptism of the soul.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thus to express intention to join Christ in one act of Baptism literally rather than sacramentally (which is done by the ordinary signification, by speaking &lt;em&gt;in persona Christi&lt;/em&gt;) renders the attempt at Baptism null.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If one person baptizes but intends to signify multiple persons, then either:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He speaks nonsense, because there is only one person ostensibly baptizing, and thus he has not signified &lt;em&gt;his&lt;/em&gt; act of baptizing, and thus Baptism has not been signified.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He speaks truth, but intends to signify something other than his present physical act of baptizing, opting for something else, such as &amp;ldquo;&amp;lsquo;we&amp;rsquo; are in moral unity as to your Baptism&amp;rdquo;, or &amp;ldquo;&amp;lsquo;we&amp;rsquo; authorize your Baptism&amp;rdquo;.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This statement fails expressly to identify his physical action &lt;em&gt;as being&lt;/em&gt; this desired or authorized Baptism: it only expresses &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; Baptism is desired or authorized.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accordingly, his physical act of washing the baptizand has not been distinguished from any other non-holy washing and is therefore not Christian Baptism.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sole exception to this is where &amp;ldquo;we&amp;rdquo; is understood to refer to the baptizer alone in a sort of elevated manner of expression. Again, though, this is weird and we think it should be avoided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;iii-the-invocation-of-the-triune-name&#34;&gt;III. The Invocation of the Triune Name&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The invocation of the Triune Name is necessary on account of its presence in Christ&amp;rsquo;s institution. If it be objected that Baptism in Jesus&amp;rsquo;s Name only is recorded in Acts, (i) it is denied; (ii) that we are in any case authorized for it is denied. Thus, it is irrelevant, and Baptism for us must be in the Triune Name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is necessary to use &amp;ldquo;Name&amp;rdquo; singular, to signify both the unity and trinity of God, the efficient cause of the Sacrament.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adherence to these points guarantees the acceptance of a Baptist Church&amp;rsquo;s Baptism by the rest of the Christian community. Contrariwise, deviation, even if felt personally to be acceptable, may place the baptized into a perilous state with respect to intercommunion with other Churches. For instance, most historic churches expressly reject the &amp;ldquo;we baptize&amp;rdquo; formula. Thus its use for no good reason in Baptisms is uncharitable to the baptized party, and is unneccessarily aggressive towards other Churches&amp;rsquo; settled practice, resting on undeniably good foundation, when evangelical peace ought to be our goal.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Only Proper Subjects</title>
      <link>https://philotheos.de/thoughts/only-proper-subjects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2024 21:12:18 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philotheos.de/thoughts/only-proper-subjects/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;LBCF 29.2: &amp;ldquo;Those who do actually profess repentance towards God, faith in, and obedience to, our Lord Jesus Christ, are the only proper subjects of this ordinance.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The operative phrase is &amp;ldquo;only proper subjects&amp;rdquo;. As in the case of &amp;ldquo;due administration&amp;rdquo;, this phrase is not self-defining, because &amp;ldquo;proper&amp;rdquo; could be taken in two ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Either, (a) &amp;ldquo;proper&amp;rdquo; refers to that which is &amp;ldquo;appropriate&amp;rdquo;, which pertains to congruity of the one with the other thing, the subject and the rite. It could be, therefore, that &amp;ldquo;proper&amp;rdquo; non-exclusively qualifies &amp;ldquo;subjects&amp;rdquo;, opening the category of &amp;ldquo;improper subjects&amp;rdquo;. Such improper subjects are at least subjects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This does seem a reasonable reading if the statement is considered on its own, however it would have the unfortunate effect of removing from the Confession any express limitation on the subjects of Baptism. Therefore, it is highly doubtful that this was the intention of the original authors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, (b) it could refer to belonging to Baptism, that is, only repentance-professing persons belong to Baptism, meaning it is a nullity if any other is washed in the Triune Name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any brief perusal of Particular Baptist writings makes it plain that the latter was intended. The staunchest statements on this matter abound in every tract.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is intended by the content of the qualification, &lt;em&gt;professing repentance, faith, and obedience to our Lord&lt;/em&gt;, is evidently an exposition of the word μαθητής/discipulus, as found in Nehemiah Coxe, &lt;em&gt;An Appendix to a Confession of Faith&lt;/em&gt; (1646):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[W]e therefore doe not admit any to the use of the Supper, nor communicate with any in the use of this ordinance, &lt;strong&gt;but disciples baptized&lt;/strong&gt;, lest we should have fellowship with them in their doing contrary to order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the Confession requires baptizands to be disciples, which the Particular Baptists defined as being capable of and actually professing repentance, faith, and obedience&amp;mdash;note, it does not require obedience itself, but profession of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question of repeating the ordinance is not actually treated in the Confession. However, given that Baptism is given on profession, it would at least seem unnecessary to rebaptize upon a falling away and subsequent &amp;ldquo;reprofession&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seating Baptism as a sign of present regeneration as Keach does (&lt;em&gt;Gold Refin&amp;rsquo;d&lt;/em&gt; pp82&amp;ndash;3), without making this real (which he expressly disowns), does shift much Baptist theory towards a baptized status contingent upon future interruptions, and the natural corollary of true anabaptistry.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Necessary for the Due Administration</title>
      <link>https://philotheos.de/thoughts/necessary-for-the-due-administration/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2024 20:13:24 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philotheos.de/thoughts/necessary-for-the-due-administration/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;LBCF 29.4: &amp;ldquo;Immersion, or dipping of the person in water, is necessary for the due administration of this ordinance.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That which is &amp;ldquo;due&amp;rdquo; refers to that which is required for an act to be properly performed. Properly performed itself needs to be defined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is nothing in the word &amp;ldquo;due&amp;rdquo; which contains the manner of this &amp;ldquo;proper performance&amp;rdquo;. Is it essential to the rite, such that without it the rite is not performed? Or is it possibly regarding law, not the essence but the manner of administration of the rite?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I searched for a potential scholastic Latin background to this phrase. The Latin for &amp;ldquo;necessary for the due administration&amp;rdquo; seems to be something like &lt;em&gt;necessarium est ad debitam ordinationis administrationem&lt;/em&gt;. I cannot find documents with similar phrases which realistically bear on the discussion. It is therefore a phrase of English origination, I presume.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In much formal contemporary usage, the phrase &amp;ldquo;necessary for the due administration&amp;rdquo; refers more to the surrounding circumstances than to the act itself. This is commonly (unexpectedly) seen in legal documents. Such an example might be justice being public unless some unique circumstance require this principle be set aside temporarily &amp;ldquo;for the due administration of justice&amp;rdquo;. The point is not that justice cannot be done at all, but that its administration will be severely hindered to the extent that its judgments may be called into question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this notion of &amp;ldquo;due&amp;rdquo; seems to imply that it can, if challenged, be rectified at a later point. In other words, it is not a question of certainty regarding the poor performance of the act, it is the intrusion of uncertainty regarding the act&amp;rsquo;s good outcome. For instance, judges not being well able to hear one another in deliberations does not guarentee a poor judgment; if, however, a legal penalty is later characterized as overly punitive, this can be rectified by compensation, commutation etc. at a future time, and the original act of justice was confirmed to have been muted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of Baptism, some aspects could be rectified, whilst others presumably could not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;being baptized without the Triune Name leaves the Baptism null and void, in fact just undone;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;having water sprinkled rather than being immersed could not reasonably be &amp;ldquo;rectified&amp;rdquo; without doing the whole Baptism over again, so this would surely count towards the nullity of the original event, though there are other considerations here (see below);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;faith not really being present in the baptizand, or an inner objection to the receipt of grace, could in principle be rectified by a later coming to faith, or dropping of the impediment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, when the Baptist Confession states &amp;ldquo;Immersion, or dipping of the person in water, is necessary for the due administration&amp;rdquo;, I conclude:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Immersion is the natural human action signified by βαπτίζω, was the mode used in the New Testament and early Church, and was the predominant ordinary mode in the first millennium, and thus remains the standard for Holy Baptism;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A defect in the administration which does not destroy that of which being dipped into water is a symbol does not render the administration void, though it may raise questions in general;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A theoretical example of this could be where a disabled man is baptized but the immersion is unsuccessful because only the left arm and foot are actually dipped. This should not be considered a nullity even though &amp;ldquo;the person&amp;rdquo; is not dipped.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pouring could in principle wet the man more than this and thus, though being an inferior mode of Baptism, does not destroy several aspects of the imagery including cleansing and being overwhelmed by the flow, and therefore, though &amp;ldquo;undue&amp;rdquo;, should be accepted as valid. Anecdotally, acceptance of pouring amongst confessional Baptists is common.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Out of love, if questions were to arise, they cannot be left hanging over the baptizand/baptized. The Church, with help of an Association or similar, must rule on any perceived impediment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &amp;ldquo;defect&amp;rdquo; which fails to signify the core of the original institution is a different institution. A smear from a wetted thumb is manifestly a different action from plunging into a river, and little is signified in common between the two.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whether sprinkling is justly considered adequate is a matter for debate. We would not deny a man has washed if he had a shower rather than a bath. This is because a shower is a broken pour. Is a sprinkle a broken pour? Presumably it is a broken very brief pour. The intention of the act of sprinkling is certainly to symbolize cleansing, but this mode is selected &lt;em&gt;instead of&lt;/em&gt; the one handed to us by our Lord, Whose prerogative it was to select His own preferred verbal signifier, aligning in His mind with the intended verbal action (not sprinkling).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my brief search of original-generation Particular Baptists, few would appear to admit pouring to be acceptable, and none would admit a Baptism of one lacking of present faith, since Baptism is &amp;ldquo;a Sign of present Regeneration, not Future&amp;rdquo; (Keach, &lt;em&gt;Gold Refin&amp;rsquo;d&lt;/em&gt;, p.82&amp;ndash;3.). I have my own argument as to why this is an untenable position, at least in the manner originally intended by Keach.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tertullian on Baptismal Deferment</title>
      <link>https://philotheos.de/thoughts/tertullian-on-baptismal-deferment/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Mar 2024 14:21:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philotheos.de/thoughts/tertullian-on-baptismal-deferment/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Tertullian&amp;rsquo;s treatise, or sermon perhaps, on Baptism is the earliest work dedicated to the subject. It is interesting in many ways, but perhaps one of those more hotly debated refers to his apparent notion of the deferment of Baptism in chapter 18.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In traditional Baptist polemics, this is typically taken as an expression of surprise at attempts by others to innovate the Baptism of young ones. The reading is that Tertullian was quite unaware of the Baptism of young ones and was forcefully resisting it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find this interpretation somewhat difficult. The work is a rhetorical piece in large measure, and thus his aim is not only to transfer doctrinal content but to do so in a way that moves people to behave in a certain way, and this is much better done not by gavel-dropping but by persuasion, specifically appeal to self-interest in deferment: &amp;ldquo;cunctatio baptismi &lt;em&gt;utilior&lt;/em&gt; est&amp;rdquo;. However, should Tertullian truly have considered the Baptism of little ones to have been a complete deviation from Apostolic tradition similar to the common Baptist claim, it seems incredible that he would have rested content with mere gentle persuasion on this point. He does not say, for instance, that it is &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt; to believe in the Trinity or the resurrection of the flesh in his apologetic works: he is required to say that if you deny these things you are outside of the fold. Thus, whatever Tertullian is contradicting, he does not consider it not-baptism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a second difficulty with his position, however, in that it seems unlikely, had Tertullian indeed believed the baptism of little ones to have been apostolic, that he would have counselled so strongly against it. How these two considerations are to be reconciled is for another place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;little-ones&#34;&gt;Little Ones&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A second Baptist contention is that Tertullian wasnt actually referencing infant baptism, just young child baptism. Bunsen was pædobaptist as far as I can tell:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tertullian&amp;rsquo;s opposition is to the baptism of young, growing children; he does not say one word about new-born infants. Neither does Origen, when his expressions are accurately weighed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.co.uk/books/edition/_/hwoQMuguHwYC?gbpv=1&amp;amp;pg=PA115&#34;&gt;Christianity and Mankind, ii.115&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The word Tertullian uses is &lt;em&gt;parvulus&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Itaque pro cuiusque personæ condicione ac dispositione, etiam ætate, cunctatio baptismi utilior est, præcipue tamen circa &lt;strong&gt;parvulos&lt;/strong&gt;. [&amp;hellip;] Ait quidem Dominos, &lt;em&gt;Nolite illos prohibere ad me venire&lt;/em&gt;: veniant ergo, dum adolescunt, dum discunt, dum quo veniant docentur: fiant Christiani cum Christum nosse potuerint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This word does not only reference infants but, more often, young children. I think the calque &amp;ldquo;little one&amp;rdquo; is pretty accurate as it encompasses both of these referents. The age range would be below six or seven years old, not dissimilar to the Greek παιδίον which properly refers to a little one under (conscious!) instruction. Parvulus can, though, be used to refer to new-borns (see below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is made in direct reference to that saying of our Lord:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sinite parvulos, et nolite eos prohibere ad me venire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ἄφετε τὰ παιδία καὶ μὴ κωλύετε αὐτὰ ἐλθεῖν πρός με.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is true that St. Luke introduces the little ones in this scene as &amp;ldquo;infantes&amp;rdquo; and even makes something of it (καὶ τὰ βρέφη), however it is clear that Tertullian is referencing the Matthæan account:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tertullian: [&amp;hellip;] nolite illos prohibere ad me venire&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke: sinite pueros venire ad me et nolite eos vetare talium est enim regnum Dei&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew: sinite parvulos et nolite eos prohibere ad me venire talium est enim regnum cælorum&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other vulgar uses of &lt;em&gt;parvulus&lt;/em&gt; to discern a taste for its usages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matt. 2: Et mittens eos in Bethlehem dixit ite et interrogate diligenter de puero parvulo et cum inveneritis renuntiate mihi ut et ego veniens adorem eum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isa. 9: Parvulus enim natus est nobis, et filius datus est nobis, et factus est principatus super humerum ejus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark 10: Amen dico vobis: Quisquis non receperit regnum Dei velut parvulus, non intrabit in illud. [The emphasis is on being teachable and humble, not unconscious.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1 Cor. 13: Cum essem parvulus, loquebar ut parvulus, sapiebam ut parvulus, cogitabam ut parvulus. Quando autem factus sum vir, evacuavi quæ erant parvuli.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gal. 4: Dico autem: quanto tempore hæres parvulus est, nihil differt a servo, cum sit dominus omnium, sed sub tutoribus et actoribus est&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heb. 5: Omnis enim, qui lactis est particeps, expers est sermonis justitiæ: parvulus enim est.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When parvulus refers only to an infant, it is often obvious&amp;mdash;natus est nobis&amp;mdash;or the word is being used imagistically such as in Hebrews. They may exist, but I&amp;rsquo;ve never seen babies &lt;em&gt;loquentes&lt;/em&gt;, for instance: they typically babble and splutter, not speak, so that reference is to talking, and thus reasonable, young children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The notion that Tertullian may be referring to young children down to, say, two or three years, is not without other parallels in important Fathers such as St. Gregory Nazianzen a couple of centuries later:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in respect of others I give my advice to wait till the end of the third year, or a little more or less, when they may be able to listen and to answer something about the Sacrament; that, even though they do not perfectly understand it, yet at any rate they may know the outlines; and then to sanctify them in soul and body with the great sacrament of our consecration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Περὶ δὲ τῶν ἄλλων δίδωμι γνώμην, τὴν τριετίαν ἀναμείναντας, ἢ μικρὸν ἐντὸς τούτου, ἢ ὑπὲρ τοῦτο (ἡνίκα καὶ ἀκοῦσαί τι μυστικὸν, καὶ ἀποκρίνεσθαι δυνατὸν, εἰ καὶ μὴ συνιέντα τελέως, ἀλλ&amp;rsquo; οὖν τυπούμενα), οὕτως ἁγιάζειν καὶ ψυχὰς καὶ σώματα τῷ μεγάλῳ μυστηρίῳ τῆς τελειώσεως.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://catholiclibrary.org/library/view?docId=Synchronized-EN/npnf.000377.SaintGregoryNazianzen.TheOrationonHolyBaptism.html;chunk.id=00000059&#34;&gt;Oration on Holy Baptism, 40.28&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, St. Gregory&amp;rsquo;s concern is that consciousness is better, even if not necessary, to the reception of Baptism. Of course, in the case of impending death, concerns over consciousness and future-focussed utility should not factor in: Κρεῖσσον γὰρ ἀναισθήτως ἁγιασθῆναι, ἢ ἀπελθεῖν ἀσφράγιστα καὶ ἀτέλεστα.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If emergency baptism pulled the age of Baptism lower over time as it developed, these data points seem to fit the trend.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Problem of Dipping Infants Anglicanism</title>
      <link>https://philotheos.de/thoughts/the-problem-of-dipping-infants-anglicanism/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Feb 2023 17:01:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philotheos.de/thoughts/the-problem-of-dipping-infants-anglicanism/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-problem-of-dipping-infants&#34;&gt;The Problem of Dipping Infants&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was recently in two old Anglican Churches and as always was fascinated by the visible architectural history. In Lancaster Priory, the effect of the Tractarians was clearly visible, confirmed by a very old photograph of the plainer Evanglical set-up from the 1800s. One of the more interesting aspects was the size of the old fonts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also at Lancaster Priory there were two fonts. The newer font had a rather grandiose 17th century lid (see below), but from the height. width, and thickness of the walls of the new stone font, it was clear that it was intended only as a receptacle for water rather than the reception of anything much larger. The font is newer than the cover, dated to 1858.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the interesting thing was hidden away, at the time behind an oversized Nativity, in a hole which was evidently formerly a staircase (black oval). In that gap, like a tragic rejected son, was a much larger and apparently more ancient font haphazardly stored which had suffered a significant blow and whose wall on one side was collapsed. This font, however, was much lower and considerably wider than the modern 19th century font. It seems clear to me that it was intended to receive the infant whole. Given the age of the Priory, it was likely cut between 1100&amp;ndash;1500.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://philotheos.de/media/prioryfont.gif&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;h4&gt;The &amp;#39;modern&amp;#39; font at Lancaster Priory.&lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a similar story to a Church I visited on account of its notorious Bishop-elect presiding. The font was likewise comparatively sizeable, and old. It is dated to at least ~1550.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&#34;http://justus.anglican.org/resources/bcp/1552/Baptism_1552.htm&#34;&gt;1552 Book of Common Prayer&lt;/a&gt;, the rubrics for the carrying out of Holy Baptism are thus:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;¶ &lt;em&gt;Then the Priest shal take the childe in his handes, and aske the name: and naming the chyld, shal dippe it in the water, so it be discretely and warely done, sayinge.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;N.&lt;/strong&gt; I Baptyse thee in the name of the father, and of the sonne, and of the holy ghost. Amen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;¶ &lt;em&gt;And yf the child be weke, it shall suffyce to power water upon it sayinge the foresayde wordes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;N.&lt;/strong&gt; I Baptyse thee in the name of the father, and of the sonne, and of the holy ghost. Amen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus the default form of the rite is &lt;strong&gt;dipping&lt;/strong&gt;, though sprinkling is permitted out of charity for a weak infant. This is not disimilar to the order in the Didache where immersion in running water is ideal, but various other options are also given if necessity demand it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The form of 1552 is also &lt;a href=&#34;http://justus.anglican.org/resources/bcp/1662/baptism.pdf&#34;&gt;retained in the 1662&lt;/a&gt;, still the standard for Anglican faith and practice:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;¶ &lt;em&gt;And then naming it after them (if they ſhall certify him that the Child may well endure it) he ſhall dip it in the Water diſcreetly and warily, ſaying,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I baptize thee in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt. Amen.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;¶ &lt;em&gt;But if they certify that the Child is weak, it ſhall ſuffice to pour Water upon it, ſaying the foreſaid words,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I baptize thee in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt. Amen.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Great, so dipping is the standard for infant baptism in England up into the 17th century. But all of the fonts I see which are newer than this (the new Priory font being an example) seem to be too small for this to be safely administered. And, indeed, I have never actually seen or heard of a baby being dipped in such a service. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure whether many Anglican priests would even be aware of this standard. In the most recent (attempted) baptism I saw, the babe barely achieved a damp smudge because his incessant strong wriggling overpowered the priestess&amp;mdash;an argument in motion if I ever witnessed one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can you think of a reason why dipping infants in holy water may be problematic?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My current reading for pleasure is the &lt;em&gt;Monumenta Ritualia Ecclesiae Anglicanae&lt;/em&gt; of Maskell. On page 14 of volume 1, in an extract taken from the occasional offices of the Church of Salisbury, we read in footnote 17 attached to the rite of renewal of the holy water the following direction:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Infans in fontem si stercoret, ejice lympham. Si tantum mingat, non moveatur aqua.&amp;rdquo; Rubr. &lt;em&gt;Man. Ebor.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yep: babies are wont to poop. I do not know it yet, but I have a hunch that up through the 19th century such would be so unmannerly and quasi-scandalous&amp;mdash;socially as much as theologically&amp;mdash;that the risk of it was better avoided, prompting a transition to a universal practice of sprinkling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least there is no show that it is the theologically superior mode unlike we must suffer from other quarters. Still, would that they would revive the older practice.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>De In Baptismo Regeneratione</title>
      <link>https://philotheos.de/thoughts/de-in-baptismo-regeneratione/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2022 17:06:59 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philotheos.de/thoughts/de-in-baptismo-regeneratione/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;dē-in-baptismō-regenerātiōne&#34;&gt;Dē In Baptismō Regenerātiōne&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In quīs viīs possunt baptistæ de regenerātiōne in baptismō dīcere? Māiōritās baptistārum dīcant in nullīs, egō autem nonnullīs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prima ratiō baptistæ generāliter regenerātiōnis in baptismō nōn dīcunt est quod magis iīs placet verbæ Deī dīcere in coniūnctiō cūm regenerātiōne. Id est, ergō fidēs ex audītū audītūs autem per verbum Chrīstī (Rom. X xvii). Sī ut crēdās est audiendum, est verbum Deī rēs, quī factulātem crēdere affert, quem regenerātiō nōminant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secunda ratiō est, quod multæ baptistæ dīcunt, baptismum ipsum prædicātiō fideī hominī baptizātī sit. In coniūnctiō cūm hāc opīniō dīcere regenerātiōnis nōn prudens sit. Æquābiliter habet baptīzātus ōrātiōnem, quæ fābulam exponet dē sēnsū dē Deō eius, quī in præterītō est. Ergō crēdunt, regenerātiō iam factus sit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tertia ratiō partis iīs est, quia in persevērantiā sanctōrum crēdunt, quī nōn fēlīciter prope regenerātiōnem in baptismō sedet. Omnia, quī regenerātus sunt, in caelum venit, multī tamen, quī baptizātī sunt, nōn persevērābunt. Ut nōn paradoxam crēdere, potius credunt quod regenerātiō nōn in baptismō fīunt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quārta ratiō simpliciter est, quia baptistæ nōn valdē sacrāmentōrum (quā sacrāmenta) scrībunt. Profectō cōnfessiō optima eōrum cōnspicuus verbum vītārit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cōgitō autem fieri potest, ut regenerātiōnis in baptismō vērē ab baptistīs dictum esse, sī attentus sit. Fēlīciter dīcō in tribus viīs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a) &lt;strong&gt;sacrāmentāliter&lt;/strong&gt;: in idem viā quī dē pānō vīnōque dīcimus, dē baptismō dīcere possumus. Id est, in cēnā Dominī pānem vidēmus, dīcimus autem quoque dē corpore Chrīstī; hoc modo intellegitur &amp;ldquo;commūniō sacrāmentālī&amp;rdquo;. Ergō potest baptistæ in baptismō regenerātiōnis dīcere: cum lavācrum tum regenerātiōnem vidēmus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dē commūniōne sacrāmentālī ipsā in hīc viā cōgitēre dissentīmus ex opīniōne Pāpæ, cuius fidēs īrōnicē et necessāriō distīnctiōnem reī ac signī abolit. Sed distīnctiōnem cōnservāre possumus in uterque causīs. Sīcut regenerātiō in vītā Chrīstiānī propriē ūnus accidit, ita baptismum ūnus videntur. Ergō tōtō animō dīcimus, quod bapstismum vērē regenerātiō est.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;b) &lt;strong&gt;ecclēsiasticē&lt;/strong&gt;: cōnstat inter omnēs regenerātiō propriē ad vītam occultam pertinet. In baptismō vidēmus hīc spīrituālem rem occultam patefit, id est ab auctorītō ecclēsiæ (epīscopōrum in omnibus ecclēsiā) certē dēclārātur. Nota bene baptistæ hominēs tantum &amp;ldquo;Chrīstiānus&amp;rdquo; nōminant, quī regenerātus sunt. Hoc modo, quoad nōs, in omnibus hominibus est baptismum vērē regenerātiō.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;c) &lt;strong&gt;chāritātīve&lt;/strong&gt;: in operā eius Knots Untied scrībēbat J.C. Ryle dē themā nostrō in coniunctiōne cum lītūrgiā ecclēsiæ anglicānæ. Sententia eius erat contrā tractāriās, quī argūmentābantur, assertiō &amp;lsquo;This child is regenerate&amp;rsquo; (Hic puer regenerātus est) in lītūrgiā baptismī regenerātiōnis dēclārātiō certa sit. Dīxit Ryle, &amp;lsquo;And this being the case, the Church most wisely leans to the side of charity, assumes hopefully of each child that it receives baptism worthily, and uses language accordingly.&amp;rsquo; (p137, &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plurimum vēritātis in verbīs Ryle est. Quia pars baptizātōrum nōn persevērābunt dīcemus regenerātiō nōn semper in baptistēriō accidit, tamen ex charitāte omnia baptizātum &amp;ldquo;Chrīstiānus&amp;rdquo; nōminātis. Ratiō est, sacrāmentum adesse fidēs requīritur, quæ invīsibilis est et quæ certē nescīmus adest (aut aderit). Ergō est hic quaestiō prō pædobaptistīs valdē magna, sed etiam ab credobaptistīs, quī normāliter pōmum Spiritī in baptizātō iam vīdērunt, cōgitandus est.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cogitō, ex charitāte, regenerātiōnis omnium baptizātōrum (id est, propter baptismum ipsum) dīcere possumus &amp;ndash; id est, sciliter nisi excommūnicātī sint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/knotsuntied00ryleuoft/page/n147/mode/2up&#34;&gt;https://archive.org/details/knotsuntied00ryleuoft/page/n147/mode/2up&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
      
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

