<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Genesis 3 on Philotheos</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/genesis-3/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Genesis 3 on Philotheos</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2021 10:06:19 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/genesis-3/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Genesis 3.16 vs Genesis 4.7</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/thoughts/genesis-3.15-vs-genesis-4.7/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2021 10:06:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/thoughts/genesis-3.15-vs-genesis-4.7/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;genesis-316-vs-genesis-47&#34;&gt;Genesis 3.16 vs Genesis 4.7&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The parallelism between the curse on Eve and the curse on Cain is an intentional juxtaposition, being only a dash of the eyes apart on a Torah scroll. However, I had not before noticed the subtle difference between them. This underlines how easy it is to overlook something clear when your preconceptions don&amp;rsquo;t align with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us rethink these important verses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;comparison-of-the-hebrew&#34;&gt;Comparison of the Hebrew&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The curse to the serpent:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will put enmity between you and the woman, and between your offspring and her offspring; he &lt;strong&gt;shall bruise&lt;/strong&gt; your head, and you &lt;strong&gt;shall bruise&lt;/strong&gt; his heel. (Genesis 3.15, ESV)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;וְאֵיבָ֣ה  אָשִׁ֗ית  בֵּֽינְךָ֙  וּבֵ֣ין  הָֽאִשָּׁ֔ה  וּבֵ֥ין  זַרְעֲךָ֖  וּבֵ֣ין  זַרְעָ֑הּ  ה֚וּא  &lt;strong&gt;יְשׁוּפְךָ֣&lt;/strong&gt;  רֹ֔אשׁ  וְאַתָּ֖ה  &lt;strong&gt;תְּשׁוּפֶ֥נּוּ&lt;/strong&gt;  עָקֵֽב׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The curse to Eve:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To the woman he said,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I will surely multiply your pain in childbearing;
in pain you shall bring forth children.
Your desire (shall be) &lt;strong&gt;contrary to&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; your husband,
but he &lt;strong&gt;shall rule&lt;/strong&gt; over you.” (Genesis 3.16, ESV)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;אֶֽל־  הָאִשָּׁ֣ה  אָמַ֗ר  הַרְבָּ֤ה  אַרְבֶּה֙  עִצְּבֹונֵ֣ךְ  וְהֵֽרֹנֵ֔ךְ  בְּעֶ֖צֶב  תֵּֽלְדִ֣י  בָנִ֑ים  &lt;strong&gt;וְאֶל־  אִישֵׁךְ֙&lt;/strong&gt;  תְּשׁ֣וּקָתֵ֔ךְ  וְה֖וּא  &lt;strong&gt;יִמְשָׁל־  בָּֽךְ׃&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The curse to Cain:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you do well, will you not be accepted? And if you do not do well, sin is crouching at the door. &lt;strong&gt;Its desire (is) contrary to&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; you&lt;/strong&gt;, but you &lt;strong&gt;must rule&lt;/strong&gt; over it.” (Genesis 4.7, ESV)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;הֲלֹ֤וא  אִם־  תֵּיטִיב֙  שְׂאֵ֔ת  וְאִם֙  לֹ֣א  תֵיטִ֔יב  לַפֶּ֖תַח  חַטָּ֣את  רֹבֵ֑ץ  &lt;strong&gt;וְאֵלֶ֙יךָ֙&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;תְּשׁ֣וּקָתֹ֔ו&lt;/strong&gt;  וְאַתָּ֖ה  &lt;strong&gt;תִּמְשָׁל־&lt;/strong&gt;  בֹּֽו׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Immediately, we see that the sense of both Eve&amp;rsquo;s curse and the Protoevangelium is &amp;ldquo;shall&amp;rdquo;, whereas &amp;ldquo;must&amp;rdquo;/&amp;ldquo;should&amp;rdquo; are used in Cain&amp;rsquo;s. But why this difference, is it justified, and what can we learn from it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;so-why-the-difference-in-translation&#34;&gt;So why the difference in translation?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, the operative verbs all take the same basic form (Qal imperfect). The difference in the rendering is an interpretative one, not a grammatical one. I do think this has bearing on our understanding of the relation of the two important verses (3.16, 4.7).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One immediate point to be drawn out of this comparison is that Cain&amp;rsquo;s (and by extension all fallen men) ruling over sin is not a foregone conclusion (&amp;ldquo;shall&amp;rdquo;) but rather a goal to be pursued, yet whose attainment is by no means certain (&amp;ldquo;must&amp;rdquo;). Perhaps it can be attained by God&amp;rsquo;s grace, or perhaps even then it cannot be in an ultimate sense (see also: our need of a Saviour).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contrariwise, the husband&amp;rsquo;s ruling over the wife is stated as a mere fact (&amp;ldquo;shall&amp;rdquo;), rather than whether or not that &amp;ldquo;should&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;must&amp;rdquo; be the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact I believe the translational difference to be unhelpful. I think these verses are indicating the postlapsarian order, which is to be accepted as something to exist within rather than something to be overcome. The order is something which should remind us of the Fall, our subjection to sin, and our need of a Saviour. This also fits with the immediate context of 3.15 and the promise of ultimate victory by the Seed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The statement is that of an order which has been operative since the Fall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-is-this-relevant&#34;&gt;Why is this relevant?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This latter point is the one which stood out to me as relevant. Much &amp;ldquo;egalitarian-complementarian&amp;rdquo; dialogue focuses on a few texts including these. The equalist view is that all ruling of the husband over the wife is a post-Fall curse, one which we must work to overcome. It is not ultimately right or fair, and is, in fact, a result of moral failing in the man. He must seek liberation from sin and its effects, which then entails a leaving behind of this sinful tendency capriciously to rule over his wife. &amp;ldquo;Capriciously&amp;rdquo; is derived from an analogy between personified &amp;ldquo;sin&amp;rdquo; (4.7), seeking to devour and destroy (1 Peter 5:8), and the husband (3.16).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take, for example, a couple of tenets from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cbeinternational.org/content/cbes-mission&#34;&gt;Christians for Biblical Equality&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Patriarchy (male dominance) is not a biblical ideal but &lt;em&gt;a result of sin&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Patriarchy is an &lt;em&gt;abuse of power&lt;/em&gt;, taking from females what God has given them: their dignity, and freedom, their leadership, and often their very lives.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be sure, there is some validity to this view. It certainly seems as though the rule of the husband is now to be harsher &amp;ndash; especially when taken together given the woman&amp;rsquo;s affliction. There is much admonition in the Epistles regarding the charge upon husbands actively to love their wives (Ephesians 5.25), not being harsh with them (Colossians 3.19), etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the main thrust of the claim, specifically that the woman&amp;rsquo;s subjection is entirely an artefact of sin, a thing to be overcome, is spoken against in a number of texts, perhaps most lucidly in 1 Corinthians 11, where the order is stated, and the supporting references are to Creation not to Fall:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I want you to understand that the head of every man is Christ, and the head of the woman is man, and the head of Christ is God&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For just as woman came from man, so also man is born of woman. But everything comes from God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;squaring-this-with-modern-feminist-life&#34;&gt;Squaring this with modern Feminist life&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But perhaps we could rather invert the Feminist critique. Perhaps we could read the chastisement to the man as his receiving the charge of having to rule over a disobedient and obstinate subordinate who is entiving, and yet whose desire is perpetually &amp;ldquo;against&amp;rdquo; him. And that the man is insufficiently equipped in and of himself for this task, just as men and women are insufficiently equipped for the task of ruling over sin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems to me that the meaning of 4.7 is that there will be perpetual struggle between us and sin, preventing perfect peace in this world. Similarly, there will be perpetual struggle between the man and his wife &amp;ndash; and men and women more generally &amp;ndash; with resentment and a desire to devour residing in the woman, and the weak and incapable man failing to rule well, resorting to temper, harsh words, and other unbecoming means. Nevertheless, the key point is that errors in carrying out the charge do not invalidate the charge on the man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is this to say that the words to the woman are likewise commands to be obeyed? Not exactly, because by analogy the words to the woman are the words regarding personified sin, whereas the words to the man are analogous with the requirement for &lt;em&gt;both man and woman&lt;/em&gt; to rule over and defeat sin. Therefore, the charge to the man in Genesis 3.16 to &amp;ldquo;rule over&amp;rdquo; is a positive requirement, even if it may be done harshly, sinfully, without love. If it were done in such a way, it would be the opposite of ruling over sin!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It appears that in the modern West, women have sought to, and and succeeded in, undo(ing) their chastisement in childrearing through various means (contraception, abortion, genetic selection of embryos, 100% pain relief, all-day childcare/schooling funded by third parties, &amp;hellip;). And men likewise have largely relieved themselves of their own burden, allowing the development of our current state of affairs where any exercise of authority by a man over a woman is immediately suspect. I will not date this post by referencing contemporary events, however a flagrant example of this is occurring as I write.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, just observing the world as it is, it would appear that the afflicitions pronounced on man and woman have in fact been overturned, and we are living in an inverted order. Some would call this liberation, others might term it hell. Does this have any bearing on the meaning of the text at this point?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems to me that whichever is the better translation, the order described in Genesis 3.16 is one which ultimately cannot be overcome, at least not in the manner attempted in our modern age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the true parallel between 3.16 and 4.7 is that just as we shall never overcome sin or the effects of sin in this life, so neither will the man rule his wife perfectly, which is to say she will never be perfectly submissive to his rule, until the Eternal State when such interactions/relations are done away with (Matthew 22.30, Revelation 21.27).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I don&amp;rsquo;t see the interpretative translations as helpful, except possibly for the reader who is looking at verses in isolation without seeking the bigger picture. Given that the parallelism is obviously intentional, it would be better to translate consistently, using footnotes if needed, and as is done in the ESV&amp;rsquo;s case with the adversative &amp;ldquo;el&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I will point out that the English &amp;ldquo;shall&amp;rdquo; can have undertones of a requirement more aligned with &amp;ldquo;must&amp;rdquo; similar to the Hebrew Qal imperfect. This is most clear in the Decalogue, where all translations aside from the NET and NLT happily use &amp;ldquo;shall&amp;rdquo; for this construction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ordinarily, &amp;ldquo;el&amp;rdquo; (אֵל) would denote motion towards, but the ESV consistently opts for the adversative meaning (&lt;strong&gt;contrary to&lt;/strong&gt;), perhaps for analogy with Genesis 4.8 (&amp;ldquo;rose up &lt;strong&gt;against&lt;/strong&gt; (el) Abel&amp;rdquo;).&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
      
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

