<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Thoughts on Philotheos</title>
    <link>https://philotheos.de/thoughts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Thoughts on Philotheos</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 Oct 2022 17:06:03 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://philotheos.de/thoughts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Sententia Zuinglii De Eucharistia</title>
      <link>https://philotheos.de/thoughts/sententia-zuinglii-de-eucharistia/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Oct 2022 17:06:03 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philotheos.de/thoughts/sententia-zuinglii-de-eucharistia/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;sententia-zuinglii-de-eucharistia&#34;&gt;Sententia Zuinglii De Eucharistia&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dictus est a multis, quod humile erat Zuinglii Reformatoris Helvetiæ iudicium de Eucharistia. Inter Protestantum video normaliter quasi scalam cum Luthero in summo, Calvino in medio, et Zwinglio ita humili, ut digiti eius rutilant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quæstio est, utrum vel quomodo Christus in Cœna adsit. Audivi, quod Zuinglius credit, panis ac vinum solummodo &lt;em&gt;symboli&lt;/em&gt; carni ac sanguinis Christi sint, in distinctione sententia Calvini, qui credit Christus certe &lt;em&gt;spiritualiter&lt;/em&gt; et &lt;em&gt;sacramentaliter&lt;/em&gt; adest, sed non &lt;em&gt;carnaliter&lt;/em&gt; vel &lt;em&gt;corporaliter&lt;/em&gt; (quia corpus Christi in Cælo est, et erit usque ad parousiam, Ioh 17.11).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hodie autem legi eius Expositionem fidei Christianæ&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; et videtur sententia eius non tam humilis quam dicunt. Quid dicis?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In una sectione appendicis declarat Zuinglius firme contra receptam opinionem, quod in Eucharistia vana et inana symbola videmus, id est Christus nullo realo modo adest:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quomodo Chriſtus ſit in cœna: Chriſtus credimus uere eſſe in cœna, imò non credimus eſſe domini cœnam niſi Chriſtus adſit. Confirmatur: Matt 18.20.  [37 sin.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pro eum necesse est, Christus in Cœna adsit, ut Cœna &lt;em&gt;eius&lt;/em&gt; esse. Euchastia nostra non est Cœnam procul ab Christo, sed, esse Cœna Domini, necesse est, quod Dominus ad nostris adsit. Vero Christus Dominus Cœnæ est, et supra eo præsidet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Posteriore sectione, fastidium carnalium mandicationis confirmat ex Ioh 6, Augustino, et Luk 7.6. Dicendum est eius emphasis aliquanto magis negativam erga Romano-Catholicam notionem quam Calvini (vide infra), et fieri potest ut hæc valida repudiatio transubstantiationis a multis sumpta sit ad totam reiectionem præsentiæ realis Christi, et sacramentalis edentis. Mihi tamen fallax videtur propter vim verborum Zuinglii in Expositione, ubi Zuinglius nihil aliud dicit quam verba Unionis Sacramentalis constitutiva. Calvinus mihi videtur incumbere tam prope ad manducationem physicam mysteriam (id est Lutheri opinionem) quam sine ullo detrimento realitatis cælestis loci Christi præsentiæ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sed si Christus in Cœna adest, quomodo Christus adest, quomodo editur?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Postea in tractatu, Zuinglius &amp;ldquo;summam&amp;rdquo; suæ sententiæ in Eucharista præbet [&lt;em&gt;sic&lt;/em&gt;]:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hæc eﬅ ſūma ſententiæ noﬅræ in Euchariﬅia: Adſerimus igitur non ſic carnaliter &amp;amp; craſſe manducari corpus Chriﬅi in cœna ut iﬅi perhibent, ſed uerum Chriﬅi corpus credimus in cœna ſacramentaliter &amp;amp; ſpiritualiter edi, à religioſa, fideli, et ſancta mente, quomodo &amp;amp; diuus Chryſoﬅomus ſentit. Et hæc eﬆ breuis ſumna noﬅræ, imò non noﬅræ ſed ipſius ueritatis, ſententiæ de hac controuerſia. [38 sin.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Credit Zuinglius manifeste Christum ipsum editur, sed non carnaliter: sacramentaliter et spiritualiter a religiosa et sancta &lt;em&gt;mente&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Videtur sententia Zuinglii nihil aliud est quam Calvini, etsi in planioribus verbis:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Summa sit, non aliter &lt;em&gt;animas&lt;/em&gt; nostras carne et sanguine Christi pasci, quam panis et vinum &lt;em&gt;corporalem&lt;/em&gt; vitam tuentur et sustinent. [&amp;hellip;] Etsi autem incredibile videtur in tanta locorum distantia penetrare ad nos Christi carnem ut nobis sit in cibum, meminerimus quantum supra sensus omnes nostros emineat arcana Spiritus sancti virtus, et quam stultum sit eius immensitatem modo nostro velle metiri. [&amp;hellip;] Itaque si per fractionem panis Dominus corporis sui participationem vere repraesentat, minime dubium esse debet, quin vere prasetet atque exhibeat. (Inst. IIII.xvii.10)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certe est, rationem bonam est, quod Zuinglii aliter loquitur, sed ipse non scio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A.D. MDXXXVI. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.co.uk/books/edition/Expositio_fidei_Christianae/2bBTAAAAcAAJ&#34;&gt;https://www.google.co.uk/books/edition/Expositio_fidei_Christianae/2bBTAAAAcAAJ&lt;/a&gt;. Mihi videtur typis non optime est.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dē In Baptismō Regenerātiōne</title>
      <link>https://philotheos.de/thoughts/de-in-baptismo-regeneratione/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2022 17:06:59 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philotheos.de/thoughts/de-in-baptismo-regeneratione/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;dē-in-baptismō-regenerātiōne&#34;&gt;Dē In Baptismō Regenerātiōne&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: kindly treat both form and content with charity!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In quīs viīs possunt baptistæ de regenerātiōne in baptismō dīcere? Māiōritās baptistārum dīcant in nullīs, egō autem nonnullīs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prima ratiō baptistæ generāliter regenerātiōnis in baptismō nōn dīcunt est quod magis iīs placet verbæ Deī dīcere in coniūnctiō cūm regenerātiōne. Id est, ergō fidēs ex audītū audītūs autem per verbum Chrīstī (Rom. X xvii). Sī ut crēdās est audiendum, est verbum Deī rēs, quī factulātem crēdere affert, quem regenerātiō nōminant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secunda ratiō est, quod multæ baptistæ dīcunt, baptismum ipsum prædicātiō fideī hominī baptizātī sit. In coniūnctiō cūm hāc opīniō dīcere regenerātiōnis nōn prudens sit. Æquābiliter habet baptīzātus ōrātiōnem, quæ fābulam exponet dē sēnsū dē Deō eius, quī in præterītō est. Ergō crēdunt, regenerātiō iam factus sit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tertia ratiō partis iīs est, quia in persevērantiā sanctōrum crēdunt, quī nōn fēlīciter prope regenerātiōnem in baptismō sedet. Omnia, quī regenerātus sunt, in caelum venit, multī tamen, quī baptizātī sunt, nōn persevērābunt. Ut nōn paradoxam crēdere, potius credunt quod regenerātiō nōn in baptismō fīunt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quārta ratiō simpliciter est, quia baptistæ nōn valdē sacrāmentōrum (quā sacrāmenta) scrībunt. Profectō cōnfessiō optima eōrum cōnspicuus verbum vītārit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cōgitō autem fieri potest, ut regenerātiōnis in baptismō vērē ab baptistīs dictum esse, sī attentus sit. Fēlīciter dīcō in tribus viīs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a) &lt;strong&gt;sacrāmentāliter&lt;/strong&gt;: in idem viā quī dē pānō vīnōque dīcimus, dē baptismō dīcere possumus. Id est, in cēnā Dominī pānem vidēmus, dīcimus autem quoque dē corpore Chrīstī; hoc modo intellegitur &amp;ldquo;commūniō sacrāmentālī&amp;rdquo;. Ergō potest baptistæ in baptismō regenerātiōnis dīcere: cum lavācrum tum regenerātiōnem vidēmus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dē commūniōne sacrāmentālī ipsā in hīc viā cōgitēre dissentīmus ex opīniōne Pāpæ, cuius fidēs īrōnicē et necessāriō distīnctiōnem reī ac signī abolit. Sed distīnctiōnem cōnservāre possumus in uterque causīs. Sīcut regenerātiō in vītā Chrīstiānī propriē ūnus accidit, ita baptismum ūnus videntur. Ergō tōtō animō dīcimus, quod bapstismum vērē regenerātiō est.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;b) &lt;strong&gt;ecclēsiasticē&lt;/strong&gt;: cōnstat inter omnēs regenerātiō propriē ad vītam occultam pertinet. In baptismō vidēmus hīc spīrituālem rem occultam patefit, id est ab auctorītō ecclēsiæ (epīscopōrum in omnibus ecclēsiā) certē dēclārātur. Nota bene baptistæ hominēs tantum &amp;ldquo;Chrīstiānus&amp;rdquo; nōminant, quī regenerātus sunt. Hoc modo, quoad nōs, in omnibus hominibus est baptismum vērē regenerātiō.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;c) &lt;strong&gt;chāritātīve&lt;/strong&gt;: in operā eius Knots Untied scrībēbat J.C. Ryle dē themā nostrō in coniunctiōne cum lītūrgiā ecclēsiæ anglicānæ. Sententia eius erat contrā tractāriās, quī argūmentābantur, assertiō &amp;lsquo;This child is regenerate&amp;rsquo; (Hic puer regenerātus est) in lītūrgiā baptismī regenerātiōnis dēclārātiō certa sit. Dīxit Ryle, &amp;lsquo;And this being the case, the Church most wisely leans to the side of charity, assumes hopefully of each child that it receives baptism worthily, and uses language accordingly.&amp;rsquo; (p137, &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plurimum vēritātis in verbīs Ryle est. Quia pars baptizātōrum nōn persevērābunt dīcemus regenerātiō nōn semper in baptistēriō accidit, tamen ex charitāte omnia baptizātum &amp;ldquo;Chrīstiānus&amp;rdquo; nōminātis. Ratiō est, sacrāmentum adesse fidēs requīritur, quæ invīsibilis est et quæ certē nescīmus adest (aut aderit). Ergō est hic quaestiō prō pædobaptistīs valdē magna, sed etiam ab credobaptistīs, quī normāliter pōmum Spiritī in baptizātō iam vīdērunt, cōgitandus est.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cogitō, ex charitāte, regenerātiōnis omnium baptizātōrum (id est, propter baptismum ipsum) dīcere possumus &amp;ndash; id est, sciliter nisi excommūnicātī sint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/knotsuntied00ryleuoft/page/n147/mode/2up&#34;&gt;https://archive.org/details/knotsuntied00ryleuoft/page/n147/mode/2up&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Psalms 9 and 10 Are They Really Acrostic</title>
      <link>https://philotheos.de/thoughts/psalms-9-and-10-are-they-really-acrostic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2022 11:16:44 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philotheos.de/thoughts/psalms-9-and-10-are-they-really-acrostic/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;psalms-9-and-10-are-they-really-acrostic&#34;&gt;Psalms 9 and 10: Are They Really Acrostic?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One cause of the numbering differences between the Septuagint (LXX) and Hebrew Psalms is the union in the LXX of Psalms 9 and 10. This is argued to be the original form of the Psalm(s) on the basis of their generally similar content as well as the lack of ascription to David in Psalm 10 which is present in the surrounding Psalms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One further hint that they may have been one is given that 9 is said to flow into 10 as an acrostic. If this be the case, it would indeed seem strange for Psalm 10 to begin its acrostic half-way through the alphabet if it weren&amp;rsquo;t originally part of Psalm 9.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is Psalm 9 with acrostic elements lettered according to my best attempt:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div dir=&#34;rtl&#34;&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1 למנצח עלמות לבן מזמור לדוד׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aאודה יהוה בכל־לבי אספרה כל־נפלאותיך׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2 (?A)אשמחה ואעלצה בך אזמרה שמך עליון׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3 Bבשוב־אויבי אחור יכשלו ויאבדו מפניך׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4 כי־עשית משפטי ודיני ישבת לכסא שופט צדק׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5 Cגערת גוים אבדת רשע שמם מחית לעולם ועד׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6 Eהאויב ׀ תמו חרבות לנצח וערים נתשת אבד זכרם המה׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;7 Fויהוה לעולם ישב כונן למשפט כסאו׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;8 והוא ישפט־תבל בצדק ידין לאמים במישרים׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;9 ויהי יהוה משגב לדך משגב לעתות בצרה׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10 ויבטחו בך יודעי שמך כי לא־עזבת דרשיך יהוה׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;11 Gזמרו ליהוה ישב ציון הגידו בעמים עלילותיו׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;12 כי־דרש דמים אותם זכר לאש־כח צעקת [עניים כ] (ענוים׃ ק)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;13 Hחננני יהוה ראה עניי משנאי מרוממי משערי מות׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;14 למען אספרה כל־תהלתיך בשערי בת־ציון אגילה בישועתך׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;15 Iטבעו גוים בשחת עשו ברשת־זו טמנו נלכדה רגלם׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;16 נודע ׀ (?J)יהוה משפט עשה בפעל כפיו נוקש רשע הגיון סלה׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;17 Jישובו רשעים לשאולה כל־גוים שכחי אלהים׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;18 Kכי לא לנצח ישכח אביון תקות [ענוים כ] (עניים ק) תאבד לעד׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;19 קומה יהוה אל־יעז אנוש ישפטו גוים על־פניך׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;20 שיתה יהוה ׀ מורה להם ידעו גוים אנוש המה סלה׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is missing a Dalet, but it is not bad. I appreciate the ease of composition for the Waw lines resulted in four in succession.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Psalm 10:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div dir=&#34;rtl&#34;&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1 Lלמה יהוה תעמד ברחוק תעלים לעתות בצרה׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2 בגאות רשע ידלק עני יתפשו ׀ במזמות זו חשבו׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3 כי־הלל רשע על־תאות נפשו ובצע ברך נאץ ׀ יהוה׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4 רשע כגבה אפו בל־ידרש אין אלהים כל־מזמותיו׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5 יחילו [דרכו כ] (דרכיו ׀ ק) בכל־עת (?M)מרום משפטיך מנגדו כל־צורריו יפיח בהם׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6 אמר בלבו בל־אמוט לדר ודר אשר לא־ברע׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;7 אלה פיהו מלא ומרמות ותך תחת לשונו עמל ואון׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;8 ישב ׀ במארב חצרים במסתרים יהרג (?N)נקי (?P)עיניו לחלכה יצפנו׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;9 יארב במסתר ׀ כאריה בסכה יארב לחטוף (?P)עני יחטף עני במשכו ברשתו׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10 [ודכה כ] (ידכה ק) ישח ונפל בעצומיו [חלכאים כ] (חיל ק) (כאים׃ ק)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;11 אמר בלבו שכח אל הסתיר (?Q)פניו בל־ראה לנצח׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;12 Sקומה יהוה אל נשא ידך אל־תשכח [עניים כ] (ענוים׃ ק)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;13 על־מה ׀ נאץ רשע ׀ אלהים אמר בלבו לא תדרש׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;14 Tראתה כי־אתה ׀ עמל וכעס ׀ תביט לתת בידך עליך יעזב חלכה יתום אתה ׀ היית עוזר׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;15 בר זרוע רשע ורע תדרוש־רשעו בל־תמצא׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;16 יהוה מלך עולם ועד אבדו גוים מארצו׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;17 Vתאות ענוים שמעת יהוה תכין לבם תקשיב אזנך׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;18 לשפט יתום ודך בל־יוסיף עוד לערץ אנוש מן־הארץ׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think clutching at straws describes Psalm 10. M, N, and the second P are actually on the atnach and are unlikely(?) to be real, whilst Q is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; right after it and so would seem to serve no purpose as part of a mnemonic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alter in his translation complains the text Masoretic of Psalm 10 is horribly mangled which may obscure an older form. If it was originally a continuation of the acrostic, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t particularly look to be any more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps that&amp;rsquo;s why it was split? Then one must invent a reason why only the second half of the Psalm was mangled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;O. Palmer Robertson, in a footnote on page 79 of his book &lt;em&gt;The Flow of the Psalms&lt;/em&gt;, argues the thematic unity of Psalms 9 and 10 &amp;ldquo;strongly [supports] the idea of a unified rather than &amp;lsquo;broken&amp;rsquo; poem&amp;rdquo;. However, that doesn&amp;rsquo;t actually answer why the acrostic is broken (his argument seems to confuse the brokenness of the Psalms into two and the brokenness of the acrostic).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, if the acrostic was originally complete, as the form would strongly suggest, would it not make more sense to conclude the lacuna was replenished with fitting content, possibly drawing from the remnants of what could be salvaged from the original, but, due to a conservative tendency of not wanting to recreate the acrostic (or not even noticing it??), that content had to be left in an inappropriate form? If that is the best the scribe could do, is that a problem?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Baptists and the Christian Tradition (Emerson) Review</title>
      <link>https://philotheos.de/thoughts/baptists-and-the-christian-tradition-emerson-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2022 08:54:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philotheos.de/thoughts/baptists-and-the-christian-tradition-emerson-review/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;baptists-and-the-christian-tradition-emerson-review&#34;&gt;Baptists and the Christian Tradition (Emerson) Review&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was much discussion in the 20&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century on the question of Baptist origins and the interplay of Baptist theology and practice with historic Christianity. In the last generation, this discussion has to some extent merged with a more general Protestant &lt;em&gt;ressourcement&lt;/em&gt; and self-appropriation of &amp;ldquo;catholic&amp;rdquo; Protestant identity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is no doubt partly due to the squeezing together of the various denominational traditions due to the pressures of modernity and totalizing secularism, however it is clear that there are good reasons from within the Protestant, including Baptist, tradition itself to rediscover the (Western) catholic elements which shaped the traditions in the 16&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; and 17&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; centuries, and use these insights to inform worship and theological inquiry today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In light of this general movement, the book &amp;ldquo;Baptists and the Christian Tradition&amp;rdquo; (ed. Emerson, Morgan, Stamps) is a compendium of essays which broadly seek to move the discussion in specifically Southern Baptist circles forward. Each essay focuses on a different theological &lt;em&gt;locus&lt;/em&gt; and the editors have done well to steer each author to keep on topic to ensure the titular theme is (for the most part) supported within each chapter. Due to the narrowness of the two Baptist traditions, there is considerable overlap in terms of the historical Baptist material presented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;General Baptists especially can, of course, be some of the most severe critics of historic practices and beliefs largely on the basis of their minimalist practice of &lt;em&gt;ad fontes&lt;/em&gt;, leapfrogging all post-apostolic literature, reducing the principle to &lt;em&gt;ad Fontem sōlum&lt;/em&gt;. Thus it is unsurprising that the (Southern Baptist) authors have more to say regarding reformation for the General Baptists than the Reformed Baptists who had a stronger chain of ancestry through to the mediæval (Western) Church. Of the historical profile of the Southern Baptists with respect to representation of these two groups I am basically ignorant, though it seems the latter are in the distinct minority today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve read the compendium with a somewhat critical eye and noted some observations for a selection of the essays. My interest is primarily in the Particular Baptists, though it is interesting by contrast to observe the diminution in theological accuracy which obtained in the case of the General Baptists, whose connexion to the broader Christian tradition has always been more tenuous. Whether or not this is causal is taken up in some of the essays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Further reviews will appear with the liberty to format and publish them.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;baptists-corporate-worship-and-the-christian-tradition&#34;&gt;Baptists, Corporate Worship, and the Christian Tradition&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;T. Worley&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Worley&amp;rsquo;s design in his essay is to argue theologically for a &amp;ldquo;recovery of historic Christian worship practices for Baptists today&amp;rdquo; (p156). This includes (i) an historical account of Baptist worship, (ii) a biblical theology of worship, and (iii) proposals for implementation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Worley fulfills his first point by analyzing the worship of the earliest Christians as a &lt;em&gt;replacement cultus&lt;/em&gt; whose acts were &amp;ldquo;simultaneously of obedience to Christ &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; of disobedience to one&amp;rsquo;s own state&amp;rdquo; (p161). That is, early worship was a replacement for a totalizing Roman religion with more simple forms inherited from Judaism, and the handing on of these specific forms may lose meaning when the religious milieu in which that worship was forged no longer obtains. Worley naturally seeks to apply his &lt;em&gt;replacement cultus&lt;/em&gt; motif to the Reformers and most especially to the Baptists in their rejection of the late-mediæval Roman religion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Worley, aided by N.T. Wright, then takes us on a journey through several Psalms to demonstrate the embedded deeply experiential aspect of our communinion with God. It is within the rhythm of life, which the Psalms excellently embody for us, that our temporal worship and the eternal heaven join one another in a union which Worley terms &amp;ldquo;liturgical time&amp;rdquo;. In the Psalms, as exemplary for our own worship, we also explore the transformation of place and the discovery of a true home of belonging. Finally, we experience during our worship an inner transformation of heart which is found in the progression of a great many of the Psalms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is no new observation that &amp;ldquo;all churches have liturgy&amp;rdquo; (p170), nor is it arguable that over the centuries Baptists have been amongst the least embracing of a more historic liturgy. Whilst there may have been good reasons for emphasizing this &amp;ldquo;freedom &lt;em&gt;from&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; in the crucible of the 17&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; and 18&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; centries, Worley argues that today we should make use of a &amp;ldquo;freedom &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; a more &amp;ldquo;reflective, theological, and missional engagement with the latent litrugical character of our worship&amp;rdquo; (p171). The design should not be &amp;ldquo;conformity&amp;rdquo; with establish traditions,&lt;side-note&gt;He lists Steven Harmon, Anthony Cross, Philip Thompson, Stanley Fowler, and others whom he assesses to be pushing this goal.&lt;/side-note&gt; but &amp;ldquo;consistency&amp;rdquo; with our own theological conclusions (p171).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, Worley contends that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extended Scripture readings should be given&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Call and response should more liberally be used (&lt;em&gt;e.g.&lt;/em&gt; &amp;ldquo;This is the Word of the Lord &amp;mdash; Thanks be to God&amp;rdquo; after a Scripture reading)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Planned movement between Invocation &amp;amp; Adoration, Confession &amp;amp; Assurance, Word &amp;amp; Table, Affirmation of Faith, and Commission and Blessing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weekly observance of the Supper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find all of these suggestions to be excellent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am unconvinced by the totality of his essay, however. In my view, the application of the &lt;em&gt;replacement cultus&lt;/em&gt; motif to Reformation religion in general, and to their worship in particular, is an error, though for some of the more radical elements which contributed to the General Baptist lineage it &lt;em&gt;may&lt;/em&gt; be applicable. For instance, the inference that &amp;ldquo;[f]rom its genesis, then, Baptist worship has been defined principally by that from which it abstains&amp;rdquo; (p163) is shown to be contradicted by the principally &lt;em&gt;positive&lt;/em&gt; statements defining worship in chapter 22 of the Confession of the Particular Baptists, especially paragraph 5. Part of the confusion appears to be the lack of distinction between the General and Particular traditions, the former of which, with its less vital connexion to the Reformation, appears to have been Worley&amp;rsquo;s primary interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likewise, his reasons for rejecting conformity to historic practices were somewhat jarring compared with other contributions in this volume. His first reason was that there is nothing to which one &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; conform, as the &amp;ldquo;image of &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; Catholic or historic church is something of a fabrication&amp;rdquo; (p172). The very existence of this volume suggests there indeed is an identifiable tradition. The second reason is that it may open Baptists up to &amp;ldquo;theological or historical idolatry&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;[c]onformity is not the Baptist way&amp;rdquo;, and &amp;ldquo;conformity would never make sense&amp;rdquo; in a &amp;ldquo;nonconformist model&amp;rdquo;. Leaving aside whether or not a nonconformist ought to conform to a &amp;ldquo;nonconformist model&amp;rdquo;, the author is merely asserting that the distinctive Baptist tradition as he sees it should box in (read: &lt;em&gt;conform&lt;/em&gt;) possible liturgical development rather than engaging substantively with the points raised by his Baptist brothers as to the deficiencies of that tradition. He may be correct to reject conformity in principle, but I am not convinced the reasons he gives make the case. In fact, given his stated reasons, I am all the more interested in his opponents&amp;rsquo; view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, Worley&amp;rsquo;s biblical argumentation regarding the rhythm of life as found in the Psalms, and a call to a renewed interest in the hymnbook of the Church, is certainly excellent and has moved at least one reader. An embracing of these understandings regarding worship will certainly provide ample justification for moving to forms which are closer aligned to those of the historic Church&amp;mdash;not necessarily because historical conformity is &lt;em&gt;per se&lt;/em&gt; desirable, but because those historic practices themselves were largely informed by the selfsame theological conclusions. To that extent, he has achieved his aims.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turretin&#39;s Citation of Bellarmine on Scripture, Corrected</title>
      <link>https://philotheos.de/thoughts/turretin-citation-bellarmine/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Nov 2021 20:00:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philotheos.de/thoughts/turretin-citation-bellarmine/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;turretins-citation-of-bellarmine-on-scripture-corrected&#34;&gt;Turretin&amp;rsquo;s Citation of Bellarmine on Scripture, Corrected&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you find yourself seeking to locate the citation of Bellarmine given by Turretin&amp;rsquo;s editors regarding the distinction of Scripture&amp;rsquo;s authority &amp;ldquo;as to itself&amp;rdquo; (quoad se) and &amp;ldquo;as to us&amp;rdquo; (quoad nos), you may encounter some difficulty. Both the publication date and chapter title are incorrect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original citation given in &lt;em&gt;Institutes&lt;/em&gt; vol. 1, p86, is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bellarmine (&amp;ldquo;De conciliis Auctoritate,&amp;rdquo; 2.12 in &lt;em&gt;Opera&lt;/em&gt; [1857], 2:61)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the book is not &amp;ldquo;de&amp;rdquo; the &lt;em&gt;councils&lt;/em&gt;, but the &lt;em&gt;authority&lt;/em&gt; of the councils. A more reliable citation seems to be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bellarmino, &lt;em&gt;Opera Omnia&lt;/em&gt;, Vol. 2, Book 2, &amp;ldquo;De Conciliorum Auctoritate&amp;rdquo;, Chapter 12, (Italy: Edente Natale Battezzati, 1858), p61.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s on Google Books:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.co.uk/books/edition/Disputationum_Roberti_Bellarmini_politan/bKZZAAAAMAAJ?hl=en&amp;amp;gbpv=0&#34;&gt;https://www.google.co.uk/books/edition/Disputationum_Roberti_Bellarmini_politan/bKZZAAAAMAAJ?hl=en&amp;amp;gbpv=0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The relevant paragraph:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diximus de auctoritate conciliorum absolute considerata;nunc de eadem dicendum est per comparationem ad alia fidei principia, idest, ad verbum Dei scriptum (nam de traditionibus eadem est ratio), et ad pontificem. Et quidem haeretici hujus temporis passim clamant, nos subjicere Scripturam conciliis. Calvinus lib. 4. instit.cap. 9. §14. &lt;strong&gt;Subjicere in eum modum,&lt;/strong&gt; inquit, &lt;strong&gt;Dei oracula hominum censurae, ut ideo rata sint, quia placuerint hominibus, blasphemia est indigna, quae commemoretur.&lt;/strong&gt; Similia apud alios passim inveniuntur. Caeterum haec non nostra blasphemia, sed ipsorum impostura est. Catholici enim Scripturam sacram non subjiciunt, sed anteponunt conciliis; neque in hoc ulla controversia est. Quod si interdum catholici aliqui dicunt, Scripturam pendere ab Ecclesia, sive a concilio, non intelligunt quoad auctoritatem, et secundum se, sed quoad explicationem, et quoad nos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the Bibtex for the more orderly among us:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;@inbook{bellarmino1858disputationum,
  title={De Conciliorum Auctoritate},
  volume={2},
  chapter={2.12}, % I.e. book 2, chapter 12.
  page={61},
  author={Bellarmino, R.F.R.},
  series={Opera Omnia},
  url={https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=bKZZAAAAMAAJ},
  year={1858},
  publisher={Edente Natale Battezzati}
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 1679 edition gives no page number so the editor clearly looked the reference up properly:&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bell.&lt;/em&gt; li. 2. de Concil. c. 12&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the 1857 edition, which I cant find, misprints the title of book 2, and was fixed in 1858.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.co.uk/books/edition/Institutio_theologiae_elencticae/jK8WAAAAQAAJ?hl=en&amp;amp;gbpv=0&#34;&gt;https://www.google.co.uk/books/edition/Institutio_theologiae_elencticae/jK8WAAAAQAAJ?hl=en&amp;amp;gbpv=0&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prayers for Holy Communion</title>
      <link>https://philotheos.de/thoughts/prayers-for-holy-communion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Jul 2021 22:21:18 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philotheos.de/thoughts/prayers-for-holy-communion/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;preparation-for-holy-communion&#34;&gt;Preparation for Holy Communion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A prayer to be used every day in the week before you receive the Holy Communion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;O BLESSED Lord Jesus Christ, Who dost bid even me, unworthy, to come unto Thee in the Blessed Sacrament of Thy Body and Blood, prepare my soul and my body, I pray Thee, to receive Thee. Give me true sorrow for my past sins, faith in Thee Who didst die upon the Cross to save me, firm purpose to keep from all that displeases Thee, and charity to forgive all who may have vexed me. Lord, come to me that Thou mayest cleanse me. Lord, come to me that Thou mayest heal me. Lord, come to me that Thou mayest strengthen me. And grant that, having received Thee, I may not forget Thee, or drive Thee from me, by being careless about pleasing Thee, but may continue Thine for ever. Amen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On Friday, or some other day before your Communion, ask yourself very carefully the following questions, first saying :&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PREVENT me, O Lord, in this and all my doings, with Thy most gracious favour, and further me with Thy continual help that in all my works begun, continued, and ended in Thee, I may glorify Thy holy Name, and finally by Thy mercy obtain everlasting life; through Jesus Christ our Lord. Amen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;O GOD of truth, make me, I pray Thee, to know myself. Pour Thy light into the dark places of my heart, that I may see my grievous sins, and tell them truly unto Thee. May I mourn for them as I ought; with a broken and a contrite heart may I confess them; and, returning to my obedience, may I be by Thee forgiven; for Jesus Christ my Saviour&amp;rsquo;s sake. Amen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Since my last Communion :&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have I fallen into any special sin, which is troubling my mind and keeping me back from God?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have I honestly tried to love and serve God?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have I said my prayers reverently and carefully every night and morning?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have I sworn or used bad words?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have I laughed and joked, or listened to others doing so, about religion and holy things?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have I been to church every Sunday and kept the rest of the day as I ought?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I have been to church have I been attentive and revent, kneeling down, etc.?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have I been honest and diligent in my work, or have I been slothful and idle, not rising in good time in the morning, or wasting my master&amp;rsquo;s or employer&amp;rsquo;s time?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have I been obdient at home and to those set over me?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have I been patient under reproof, not answering again etc.?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have I quarrelled with any one or lost my temper? thought or spoken evil of another, been unkind or sulky?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If I have quarrelled with any one, have I tried to make it up?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have I been envious of others? or proud or conceited about myself?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have I done anything impure, or said anything impure, or encouraged any impure thought?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have I taken more than I ought to eat or to drink?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have I been dishonest, or stolen anything?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have I told a lie? or deceived any one in word or act?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have I grumbled at my lot, or been discontented or covetous?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have I in any way helped or encouraged others in what is wrong?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have I been regular in my times of receiving the Holy Communion?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Was I careful about my preparation and thanksgiving at my last communion, and have I tried to keep the resolutions I then made?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Then confess you sins to God very humbly, saying :&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I CONFESS to Thee, O God, that I have sinned against Thee in thought, and word, and deed, through my fault, through my own great fault, especially by . . . (&lt;em&gt;here name the sins you have found out by self-examination&lt;/em&gt;). O Lord, give me true sorrow; forgive me these and all my many sins which I have forgotten. O let me not fall from Thee any more. I grieve for ever having offended Thee; by Thy help I will serve Thee better for the time to come; I give myself to Thee; henceforth I resolve to serve none but The; I will walk in the way of Thy commandments. Pardon all my failings, O my God, and perfect that good work which Thou hast begun in me. O grant me Thy grace, hear me, help me, and have mercy upon me. And this I ask for Jesus Christ&amp;rsquo;s sake, my Lord and Saviour. Amen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Here you may add Psalm 51.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taken from the Anglican prayer aid, &lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/HelpsToWorship/page/n29/mode/2up&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Helps to Worship&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Socrates in Acts 5</title>
      <link>https://philotheos.de/thoughts/socrates-in-acts-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2021 19:43:47 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philotheos.de/thoughts/socrates-in-acts-5/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;socrates-in-acts-5&#34;&gt;Socrates in Acts 5&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Apology of Plato&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; is the defence given by Socrates at the trial which condemned him on the dual charges of disbelieving in the gods of the city, and corrupting the youth. The defence is found in three sections, the first being his defence proper, the second his proposal for what his punishment should be, and the third his speech after having received condemnation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his first speech, Socrates makes one apparently sarcastic appeal which would seem to undermine his case, making it as though he was not truly taking proceedings seriously. Socrates had previously attempted to fend off the claims of disbelieving in the gods of the city, although it&amp;rsquo;s difficult to say he was taking their charges wholly seriously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, he then enters a section where he appeals to his δαιμόνιον as justification for rejecting the authority of the court. My limited reading in this period suggests that obedience to the civil law, and even more so to practice the law or politics, was regarded as pious and an act of religious devotion. Therefore, by appealing to the daimonion given by an external Oracle beyond the pantheon of the city&amp;rsquo;s gods, he is not only granting their claim, but he is claiming that their laws and indeed the present assembly is acting impiously. How one squares this with his strict legalism in Crito isn&amp;rsquo;t obvious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most interesting section to me, however, is when Socrates ponders whether an acceptable punishment would be for the court to release him but bind his tongue from speaking Philosophy. At this thought, Plato records:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;if you say to me, Socrates, this time we will not mind Anytus (one of his accusers), and &lt;strong&gt;will let you off, but upon one condition,&lt;/strong&gt; that are to inquire and speculate in this way any more, and that if you are caught doing this again you shall die; - if this was the condition on which you let me go, &lt;strong&gt;I should reply: Men of Athens, I honour and love you; but I shall obey God rather than you,&lt;/strong&gt; and while I have life and strength I shall never cease from the practice and teaching of philosophy, exhorting anyone whom I meet after my manner, and convincing him[&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Huh? Sounds familiar. It is almost a direct parallel to an important event which happened centuries later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comparing under-over:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Socrates: &amp;hellip;ὦ ἄνδρες Ἀθηναῖοι, ἀσπάζομαι μὲν καὶ φιλῶ, &lt;strong&gt;πείσομαι δὲ μᾶλλον τῷ θεῷ ἢ ὑμῖν&lt;/strong&gt;,&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;br&gt;
Acts 5.29: &amp;hellip;ἀποκριθεὶς δὲ πέτρος καὶ οἱ ἀπόστολοι εἶπαν &lt;strong&gt;πειθαρχεῖν δεῖ θεῷ μᾶλλον ἢ ἀνθρώποις&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only does Luke (well-read in the Greeks of Plato&amp;rsquo;s period no doubt, given his style) record the happenstance almost identically, he makes sure to use the same verb, albeit with -αρχεῖν (authorities) suffix. Even the weak adversative becomes δεῖ (it is necessary&amp;hellip;): an attempt to draw the words spoken to be as close an allusion as possible?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leads me to three options:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is pure accident&lt;/em&gt;: I suppose this is possible, but as a theory tends to imply a belitting of the Greek influence elsewhere present in New Testament thought and action.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;This manner of speaking was well-known and -used&lt;/em&gt;: Maybe this was the case precisely because of Plato&amp;rsquo;s account, or it could have entered the Greek mind even earlier, with Socrates himself making reference to it. However, this would not explain the similarity of situation as nicely as the third option.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Peter was making intentional allusion&lt;/em&gt;: The account of Socrates&amp;rsquo;s Apology was well-known, and Peter and the Apostles, and Luke recording this, made intentional subtle reference to the trial of Socrates to drive up sympathy for their cause, and to cause their persecutors to reflect on whether it was actually they themselves who were the impious ones.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The account in Acts 5 took place in Jerusalem, of course, and was presumably spoken in Aramaic(?). How influencial was Socrates&amp;rsquo; trial amongst those in Jersulem? Would they even get the reference? Is it necessary that they should get the reference, or is it sufficient that those reading the account later would? Was the stylizing just Luke&amp;rsquo;s interpreting/dramatizing of the event for his own purposes?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has certainly made me think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://classics.mit.edu/Plato/apology.html&#34;&gt;http://classics.mit.edu/Plato/apology.html&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://khazarzar.skeptik.net/books/plato/apologig.htm&#34;&gt;http://khazarzar.skeptik.net/books/plato/apologig.htm&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Early Church on Friday Fasting</title>
      <link>https://philotheos.de/thoughts/church-fathers-on-friday-fasting/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2021 08:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philotheos.de/thoughts/church-fathers-on-friday-fasting/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;early-church-on-friday-fasting&#34;&gt;Early Church on Friday Fasting&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s common to view Friday fasting, especially from meat, but also a 3pm fast, as Romanist. However, I&amp;rsquo;m not convinced it&amp;rsquo;s entirely so simple. Fasting from meat on Fridays has been fairly constant throughout Church history (not to validate it), and is common in both East and West including the Lutheran and Anglican traditions.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Wesley would not ordain a man to the Methodist ministry if he didn&amp;rsquo;t fast till 3pm Wednesdays (Christ&amp;rsquo;s betrayal) and Fridays (His Passion).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, we should consider our Lord&amp;rsquo;s words on the general topic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And &lt;strong&gt;when you fast&lt;/strong&gt;, do not look gloomy like the hypocrites, for they disfigure their faces that their fasting may be seen by others. Truly, I say to you, they have received their reward. &lt;strong&gt;But when you fast&lt;/strong&gt;, anoint your head and wash your face, that your fasting may not be seen by others but by your Father who is in secret. And your Father who sees in secret will reward you. (Matthew 6)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of this phrase &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;when&lt;/em&gt; you fast&amp;rdquo; implies that Jesus &lt;em&gt;expects&lt;/em&gt; the people He is admonishing to fast regularly, even as a matter of habit. To conclude there is friction between the above and an organized Church-wide time of fasting (where others &amp;ldquo;see&amp;rdquo; your fasting by your general obedience) is surely a misuse of this text.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;didache&#34;&gt;Didache&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;7:6 But before the baptism let him that baptizeth and him that is baptized fast, and any others also who are able;
7:7 and thou shalt order him that is baptized to fast a day or two before.
8:1 And let not your fastings be with the hypocrites, for they fast on the second and the fifth day of the week;
8:2 but do ye keep your fast on the fourth (&lt;em&gt;i.e.&lt;/em&gt; Wednesday) and on the preparation (the sixth, &lt;em&gt;i.e.&lt;/em&gt; Friday) day.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Didache (&lt;em&gt;lit.&lt;/em&gt; &amp;rsquo;teaching&amp;rsquo;) is an interesting source as it&amp;rsquo;s early (AD 50-120).&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; From the above, it&amp;rsquo;s apparent that a) regular (weekly) fasting was anything but unusual and b) (Spy) Wednesday and (Good) Friday were the chosen times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I take the chapter break to be well advised not only because of the sort of sporadic teaching section the above quotation is found in, but also because to align &amp;ldquo;fast a day or two before [baptism]&amp;rdquo; (presumably Sunday?) with &amp;ldquo;fast on Wednesdays and Fridays&amp;rdquo; would seem unnatural &amp;ndash; though admittedly not impossible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note, too, the apparent draw-down of our Lord&amp;rsquo;s phrasing, pitting Christian fasting against that of the hypocrites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sherpherd-of-hermas&#34;&gt;Sherpherd of Hermas&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-constitutes-a-fast&#34;&gt;What constitutes a &amp;ldquo;fast&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Shepherd of Hermas alludes to the actual matter of a fast, being the consumption of bread and water only:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, be on your guard against every evil word, and every evil desire, and purify your heart from all the vanities of this world. If you guard against these things, your fasting will be perfect. And you will do also as follows. Having fulfilled what is written, &lt;strong&gt;in the day on which you fast you will taste nothing but bread and water&lt;/strong&gt;; and having reckoned up the price of the dishes of that day which you intended to have eaten, you will give it to a widow, or an orphan, or to some person in want, and thus you will exhibit humility of mind, so that he who has received benefit from your humility may fill his own soul, and pray for you to the Lord.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Shepherd of Hermas III.5.3&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He then links this with saving the money that would have been spent on luxuries and counting it as alms to the poor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-constitutes-a-valid-fast&#34;&gt;What constitutes a valid fast?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SOH is careful, though, to emphasize that simply abstaining from food in this manner is of no real benefit, especially if it leads to aloofness, or the rejection of service to others. An example of his criticism of vain fasting was already given in Chapter 1 of this similitude:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;WHILE fasting and sitting on a certain mountain, and giving thanks to the Lord for all His dealings with me, I see the Shepherd sitting down beside me, and saying, “Why have you come hither [so] early in the morning?” “Because, sir,” I answered, “I have a station.” “What is a station?” he asked. “I am fasting, sir,” I replied. “What is this fasting,” he continued, “which you are observing?” “As I have been accustomed, sir,” I reply, “so I fast.” “You do not know,” he says, “how to fast unto the Lord: &lt;strong&gt;this useless fasting which you observe to Him is of no value&lt;/strong&gt;.” “Why, sir,” I answered, “do you say this?” “I say to you,” he continued, “that the fasting which you think you observe is not a fasting. But I will teach you what is a full and acceptable fasting to the Lord.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Listen,” he continued: “God does not desire such an empty fasting. For fasting to God in this way you will do nothing for a righteous life; but offer to God a fasting of the following kind: &lt;strong&gt;Do no evil in your life, and serve the Lord with a pure heart: keep His commandments, walking in His precepts, and let no evil desire arise in your heart; and believe in God&lt;/strong&gt;. If you do these things, and fear Him, &lt;strong&gt;and abstain from every evil thing&lt;/strong&gt;, you will live unto God; and if you do these things, you will keep a great fast, and one acceptable before God.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Shepherd of Hermas III.5.1&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the SOH is more concerned with the living a holy life in obedience to God&amp;rsquo;s commands than repetitious fasting which is really no fasting at all. In doing so, SOH is taking the physical principle of fasting (abstaining from things enjoyable) and applying it spiritually (abstaining from sin). Surely there is a great deal of truth in this application, and both kinds of &amp;ldquo;fasting&amp;rdquo; should be bound up together in the life of the Christian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;lessons&#34;&gt;Lessons&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The early believers clearly practised a disciplined life of fasting and prayer. The precise nature of the fast was not constant across time or space, and did not necessarily equate to a complete abstinance from food and/or water. It also seems to be a tendency of our sinful flesh to latch onto a practice such as fasting and to abuse it, either by creating mystery surrounding it, creating arbitrary rules around it, or performing the act in a self-centred way contrary to the nature of the act in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The contemporary response seems to have been one of forgetfulness &amp;ndash; how often have you even heard someone mention fasting as a thing &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; should do in the past ten yeas? &amp;ndash; probably due to a few generations of hesitancy amongst Reformed people due to abuses they have seen regarding fasting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will write a follow-up post on the practice with reference to the Reformed tradition and contemporary practice soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&#34;http://basicchristian.org/bcp-1662.pdf&#34;&gt;http://basicchristian.org/bcp-1662.pdf&lt;/a&gt;, p49.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;E.g.&lt;/em&gt; Acts 14.23, Paul and Barnabas clearly didn&amp;rsquo;t conceal their fasting, indeed it is reassuring to know they sought God with prayer and fasting. Also see &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.the1689confession.com/1689/chapter-26&#34;&gt;2LBCF 26.9&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.earlychristianwritings.com/text/didache-lightfoot.html&#34;&gt;http://www.earlychristianwritings.com/text/didache-lightfoot.html&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know if the reference to &amp;ldquo;preparation day&amp;rdquo; (c.f. Mark 15.42) is telling of this section being composed earlier. When did this terminology die out amongst the Christians?&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sherpherd of Hermas, Book 3 &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.newadvent.org/fathers/02013.htm&#34;&gt;https://www.newadvent.org/fathers/02013.htm&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Illustration in Preaching</title>
      <link>https://philotheos.de/thoughts/notes-on-illustration-in-preaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Apr 2021 13:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philotheos.de/thoughts/notes-on-illustration-in-preaching/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;notes-on-illustration-in-preaching&#34;&gt;Notes on Illustration in Preaching&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Following are notes from a seminar on the use of illustration in preaching.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Illustration is the art of illumating a thought by means of allusion to something already familiar to the hearer. Illustration in preaching is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; essential &amp;ndash; that is, preaching can be preaching without any explicit illustrations &amp;ndash; but the lack of it will almost certainly impoverish any spoken message. Some contexts where illustrations may be less needed are discussed towards the end of this session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-the-purpose-of-illustration&#34;&gt; What is the purpose of illustration?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A non-exhaustive list:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Illustrations aid understanding &amp;ndash; bringing clarity of thought, particularly though not exclusively for those less able or inclined to follow lengthy addresses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Illustration makes thoughts accessible
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some people need a hook to grab a hold of a thought&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This can occur in the act of preaching, where the preacher infers from the posture of the hearers that his point is not landing, perhaps due to some difficulty in understanding it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Illustrations create firm impressions which will last beyond the duration of the sermon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Illustrations bring conviction
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In this sense, they can be seen as a means of application.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Illustrations aid memorization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Illustration provide an opportunity for reflection
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Particularly in a denser sermon, illustrations can provide respite from the auditory onslaught, a window to enable enlightening&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Illustration aids application
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Illustration is the handmaiden of application&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Illustration is helpful for self-examination&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;illustration-is-more-than-word-pictures&#34;&gt;Illustration is more than word pictures&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many preachers will talk of illustration purely in terms of &lt;em&gt;sight&lt;/em&gt;; however, illustration should include a reaching into all five senses, recalling smells and sounds as well as sights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jay Adams is helpful in this regard. The below is inspired by his work &lt;em&gt;Preaching with Purpose: The Urgent Task of Homiletics&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jay lists several supports to his point:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Illustration is not just an appeal to sight.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Illustration should trigger the memory of sound, smell, &lt;em&gt;etc.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Illustration should appeal to the whole of human sense, including:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evocative language&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Story-telling (including mini stories)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sound (intonation and dynamics)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gesture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some examples of these four points from our Lord:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;mark-101-31&#34;&gt;Mark 10.1-31&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Story-telling&lt;/strong&gt;: Verse 25 &amp;ldquo;camel through the eye of a needle&amp;rdquo;
&lt;strong&gt;Gesture&lt;/strong&gt;: &amp;ldquo;Looking at him and loved him&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This second instance is interesting, for the love is contained in the look. Thus we can learn for our preaching that eye contact with our hearers is simply a must. &lt;em&gt;Looking&lt;/em&gt; aids the connection between preacher and hearer, and often communicates a great deal in itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;luke-121-34&#34;&gt;Luke 12.1-34&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Story-telling&lt;/strong&gt;: Parable of the Rich Fool&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evocative language&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;V1 &amp;ldquo;the &lt;em&gt;leaven&lt;/em&gt; of the Pharisees&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an intentional &lt;em&gt;misuse&lt;/em&gt; of language. Leaven itself is especially well-known to the hearers in that day, being a society whose daily need could be described as &amp;ldquo;daily bread&amp;rdquo; (Matthew 6.11). Leaven is added to the dough and works its way mysteriously through the lump (Matthew 13.33). The phrase &amp;ldquo;leaven of the &lt;em&gt;Pharisees&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; therefore immediately creates intrigue in the minds of the hearers. Then, as possible senses begin to settle in the mind, our Lord lands the blow to the midriff: &amp;ldquo;which is hypocrisy&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A similar &amp;ldquo;misuse&amp;rdquo; of language is found in v28: &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;&lt;em&gt;clothes&lt;/em&gt; the grass&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;V2-3 Juxtaposition of light and darkness&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, our Lord uses a barrage of four metaphors to elucidate the one truth:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;covered up-revealed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;hidden-known&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;dark-light&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;whispered in inner rooms-proclaimed from the rooftops&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Darkness is something we are innately wary of even from an early age. In it is mystery, chaos, and threat. Spurgeon tells the story of being in a carriage which, some time after the sun had set, was at once illuminated by the lighting of a candle by a fellow traveller. All eyes were drawn to the lightsource from instinct.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gesture&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;V6 &amp;ldquo;Consider the sparrows&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; one can well imagine the Lord gesturing to a sparrow with His hand. Perhaps some had even that moment graced a nearby tree, and drawn some hearers&amp;rsquo; attention away from His own words. &amp;ldquo;Not to worry, they too can illustrate My point&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sound&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;V32 &amp;ldquo;Fear not, little flock, &amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The meaning of &amp;ldquo;Fear not&amp;rdquo; need not only be conveyed by the &lt;em&gt;content&lt;/em&gt; of the words, but also the &lt;em&gt;manner of delivery&lt;/em&gt;. It would seem greatly incongruous for our Lord to seek to comfort a &amp;ldquo;little flock&amp;rdquo; with fearsome and harsh tonality. When the &lt;strong&gt;content&lt;/strong&gt; of our messages changes, let the &lt;strong&gt;sound&lt;/strong&gt; of our message reflect, support, and emphasize this change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;from-where-are-we-to-gather-our-illustrations&#34;&gt; From where are we to gather our illustrations? &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are those who would counsel all young preachers actively to seek out little stories and analogies to add to a &lt;strong&gt;filing system&lt;/strong&gt;. Whilst it is not wrong to do this, it is certainly not required. In fact, the seeking of an illustration in this manner may be hazardous, for if a perfect fit cannot be found, it may end up with a preacher in despair, a stodgy sermon, or a confusing illustration majoring on the incorrect point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be prompted to an illustration in the memory is likely better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To this end, we should consider that most of our illustrations shoud come &lt;strong&gt;from the Scripture&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are preachers of the Word of God which is full of stories, &lt;em&gt;let us use them&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every piece of evocative language in the Scripture is &lt;em&gt;inspired&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The content of Scripture is simply brilliant (gripping, fascinating, and true stories).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alluding to Scripture teaches and clarifies more Scripture.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Bible itself appeals to all the senses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bible was delivered to aural peoples, in contradistinction to ours of the &lt;em&gt;written&lt;/em&gt; word (or possibly, an increasingly unlettered people). To that end, it is not streching words too far to state that &lt;em&gt;all of Scripture is in some sense &lt;strong&gt;sermonic&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Potential caveat&lt;/strong&gt;: Be wise and discriminate in the use of Scriptural allusion. The point is not to refer to the lesser-trodden paths with the inevitable result of (1) not clarifying your point and (2) inculcating a feeling of inadequacy in your hearers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Draw illustrations from:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Daily life&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nature&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Personal interactions (yours and observed)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Personal experience (see below)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As preachers, our vocation is one of shepherding. Therefore, let us not see things as they appear only, but rather dig to find the root from which the behaviour originates. This is necessary if we are effectively at every opportunity to draw and shepherd our hearers on to a higher level no matter where they currently are. Stuart Olyott&amp;rsquo;s work &lt;a href=&#34;https://banneroftruth.org/uk/store/church-ministry/ministering-like-the-master/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ministering like the Master&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is particularly helpful on this point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Personal experience&lt;/strong&gt; can be a source of illustration, however it may be advisable for young preachers to avoid this for fear of drawing too much attention to the preacher rather than his point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;practical-advice&#34;&gt;Practical advice&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;reading-aloud&#34;&gt; Reading aloud&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Practice reading the Scripture as if to &lt;em&gt;be heard&lt;/em&gt;. Seek not to read the Scripture as quickly as possible. Rather, seek to embody the grammar, stress, and emphases of the text in your reading of it. In general, read aloud if at all possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;### Matthew 11 ###&#34;&gt;comment&lt;/a&gt;: &amp;lt;&amp;gt; (A whirlwind is full of sight &lt;em&gt;and sound&lt;/em&gt; (and possibly flying debris).)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;use-of-gesture&#34;&gt; Use of Gesture&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use the body to convey truth. This is not to say we should all disrobe &amp;amp; marry a harlot, or lie on the ground for however long, but these extreme inhabitations of the principle help to make it real to us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;bring-me-a-coin-mark-1215&#34;&gt; &amp;ldquo;Bring me a coin&amp;rdquo; (Mark 12.15)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our Lord&amp;rsquo;s reply to his aggressive inquirers regarding the paying of taxes was to use a physical gesture, the raising of the coin &amp;ndash; which they had: He did not &amp;ndash; in order to confound them. The physical act of showing them from their own coin His point was a communication of meaning in itself &amp;ndash; especially as they will then recall the teaching whenever they use such a coin (&lt;em&gt;i.e.&lt;/em&gt; every day). (See also: the list at the start of this session.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not necessarily to advocate the use of props.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;use-of-stories&#34;&gt;Use of stories&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We naturally latch on to stories much more than bare propositions. The use of stories can therefore greatly enhance the reception of a sermon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of extended stories is generally permissible, but the story must be very well-suited to the point at hand. The more elaborate the story, the less likely this will be obviously the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stories may be invented&lt;/strong&gt; Creating a story for a purpose is perhaps somewhat unusual but can be done with excellent effect. After all, few believe that Jesus&amp;rsquo;s Parables were retellings of real events. Have a &lt;em&gt;large degree of caution&lt;/em&gt; before embellishing any story based on Scripture, however.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sourcing stories&lt;/strong&gt; Church history and biographies are replete with useful stories. There may be a risk of hagiography in the use of biographical stories, which is distasteful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stuart Olyott brings six considerations in the use of stories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Must be subordinate to the point&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Must be clear&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ought to be brief&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Should never offend common dignity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Should be varied (&lt;em&gt;not another fishing analogy&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Must be accurate &amp;ndash; &lt;em&gt;check your sources!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-may-affect-the-amount-of-illustration-needed&#34;&gt;What may affect the amount of illustration needed&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The type or context of the sermon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if the sermon is to be heard by a great many unbelievers, referencing not-widely-known biblical stories may be unhelpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The nature of the passage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, Paul&amp;rsquo;s dense theology may be illustrated well with OT stories. However, preaching an OT narrative may require almost no illustration as the text illustrates itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Amount of practical application required&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More practical application requires less illustration, because application is inherently (personally) illustrative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;final-considerations&#34;&gt;Final considerations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoid overillustration &amp;ndash; on this, Spurgeon is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a good model!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Preaching is application, but preaching is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; illustration &amp;ndash; it is &lt;em&gt;served by&lt;/em&gt; illustration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Art of Illustration by C. H. Spurgeon&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/42558&#34;&gt;https://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/42558&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
      
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

