<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Psalm 9 on Philotheos</title>
    <link>https://philotheos.de/tags/psalm-9/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Psalm 9 on Philotheos</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 14 May 2022 11:16:44 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://philotheos.de/tags/psalm-9/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Psalms 9 and 10 Are They Really Acrostic</title>
      <link>https://philotheos.de/thoughts/psalms-9-and-10-are-they-really-acrostic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2022 11:16:44 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philotheos.de/thoughts/psalms-9-and-10-are-they-really-acrostic/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;psalms-9-and-10-are-they-really-acrostic&#34;&gt;Psalms 9 and 10: Are They Really Acrostic?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One cause of the numbering differences between the Septuagint (LXX) and Hebrew Psalms is the union in the LXX of Psalms 9 and 10. This is argued to be the original form of the Psalm(s) on the basis of their generally similar content as well as the lack of ascription to David in Psalm 10 which is present in the surrounding Psalms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One further hint that they may have been one is given that 9 is said to flow into 10 as an acrostic. If this be the case, it would indeed seem strange for Psalm 10 to begin its acrostic half-way through the alphabet if it weren&amp;rsquo;t originally part of Psalm 9.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is Psalm 9 with acrostic elements lettered according to my best attempt:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div dir=&#34;rtl&#34;&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1 למנצח עלמות לבן מזמור לדוד׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aאודה יהוה בכל־לבי אספרה כל־נפלאותיך׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2 (?A)אשמחה ואעלצה בך אזמרה שמך עליון׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3 Bבשוב־אויבי אחור יכשלו ויאבדו מפניך׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4 כי־עשית משפטי ודיני ישבת לכסא שופט צדק׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5 Cגערת גוים אבדת רשע שמם מחית לעולם ועד׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6 Eהאויב ׀ תמו חרבות לנצח וערים נתשת אבד זכרם המה׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;7 Fויהוה לעולם ישב כונן למשפט כסאו׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;8 והוא ישפט־תבל בצדק ידין לאמים במישרים׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;9 ויהי יהוה משגב לדך משגב לעתות בצרה׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10 ויבטחו בך יודעי שמך כי לא־עזבת דרשיך יהוה׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;11 Gזמרו ליהוה ישב ציון הגידו בעמים עלילותיו׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;12 כי־דרש דמים אותם זכר לאש־כח צעקת [עניים כ] (ענוים׃ ק)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;13 Hחננני יהוה ראה עניי משנאי מרוממי משערי מות׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;14 למען אספרה כל־תהלתיך בשערי בת־ציון אגילה בישועתך׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;15 Iטבעו גוים בשחת עשו ברשת־זו טמנו נלכדה רגלם׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;16 נודע ׀ (?J)יהוה משפט עשה בפעל כפיו נוקש רשע הגיון סלה׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;17 Jישובו רשעים לשאולה כל־גוים שכחי אלהים׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;18 Kכי לא לנצח ישכח אביון תקות [ענוים כ] (עניים ק) תאבד לעד׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;19 קומה יהוה אל־יעז אנוש ישפטו גוים על־פניך׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;20 שיתה יהוה ׀ מורה להם ידעו גוים אנוש המה סלה׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is missing a Dalet, but it is not bad. I appreciate the ease of composition for the Waw lines resulted in four in succession.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Psalm 10:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div dir=&#34;rtl&#34;&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1 Lלמה יהוה תעמד ברחוק תעלים לעתות בצרה׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2 בגאות רשע ידלק עני יתפשו ׀ במזמות זו חשבו׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3 כי־הלל רשע על־תאות נפשו ובצע ברך נאץ ׀ יהוה׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4 רשע כגבה אפו בל־ידרש אין אלהים כל־מזמותיו׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5 יחילו [דרכו כ] (דרכיו ׀ ק) בכל־עת (?M)מרום משפטיך מנגדו כל־צורריו יפיח בהם׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6 אמר בלבו בל־אמוט לדר ודר אשר לא־ברע׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;7 אלה פיהו מלא ומרמות ותך תחת לשונו עמל ואון׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;8 ישב ׀ במארב חצרים במסתרים יהרג (?N)נקי (?P)עיניו לחלכה יצפנו׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;9 יארב במסתר ׀ כאריה בסכה יארב לחטוף (?P)עני יחטף עני במשכו ברשתו׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10 [ודכה כ] (ידכה ק) ישח ונפל בעצומיו [חלכאים כ] (חיל ק) (כאים׃ ק)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;11 אמר בלבו שכח אל הסתיר (?Q)פניו בל־ראה לנצח׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;12 Sקומה יהוה אל נשא ידך אל־תשכח [עניים כ] (ענוים׃ ק)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;13 על־מה ׀ נאץ רשע ׀ אלהים אמר בלבו לא תדרש׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;14 Tראתה כי־אתה ׀ עמל וכעס ׀ תביט לתת בידך עליך יעזב חלכה יתום אתה ׀ היית עוזר׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;15 בר זרוע רשע ורע תדרוש־רשעו בל־תמצא׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;16 יהוה מלך עולם ועד אבדו גוים מארצו׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;17 Vתאות ענוים שמעת יהוה תכין לבם תקשיב אזנך׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;18 לשפט יתום ודך בל־יוסיף עוד לערץ אנוש מן־הארץ׃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think clutching at straws describes Psalm 10. M, N, and the second P are actually on the atnach and are unlikely(?) to be real, whilst Q is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; right after it and so would seem to serve no purpose as part of a mnemonic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alter in his translation complains the text Masoretic of Psalm 10 is horribly mangled which may obscure an older form. If it was originally a continuation of the acrostic, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t particularly look to be any more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps that&amp;rsquo;s why it was split? Then one must invent a reason why only the second half of the Psalm was mangled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;O. Palmer Robertson, in a footnote on page 79 of his book &lt;em&gt;The Flow of the Psalms&lt;/em&gt;, argues the thematic unity of Psalms 9 and 10 &amp;ldquo;strongly [supports] the idea of a unified rather than &amp;lsquo;broken&amp;rsquo; poem&amp;rdquo;. However, that doesn&amp;rsquo;t actually answer why the acrostic is broken (his argument seems to confuse the brokenness of the Psalms into two and the brokenness of the acrostic).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, if the acrostic was originally complete, as the form would strongly suggest, would it not make more sense to conclude the lacuna was replenished with fitting content, possibly drawing from the remnants of what could be salvaged from the original, but, due to a conservative tendency of not wanting to recreate the acrostic (or not even noticing it??), that content had to be left in an inappropriate form? If that is the best the scribe could do, is that a problem?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

